<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second admonition to the parliament</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110798</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846271</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846271</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11227</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11227)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 454:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second admonition to the parliament</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Stroud?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Hemel Hempstead? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1572]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dubiously attributed to Thomas Cartwright.</note>
                  <note>Caption title; imprint suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Colophon (leaf H5) reads: Imprinted we know where, and whan, Iudge you the place and you can.</note>
                  <note>Caption title (leaf H5) reads: Certaine articles, collected and taken (as it is thought) by the byshops out of a little boke entituled an Admonition to the Parliament, with an answere to the same. Containing a confirmation of the sayde booke in those notes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: *⁴ A-G⁴ H⁶ (H6 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Puritans --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:11227:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11227:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A SECOND Admonition to the Parliament.</head>
            <bibl>Ieremie. 26. 11. 12. 13. 14. 15.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>Then ſpake the Prieſtes / and the Prophets / vnto the Princes / &amp; to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people / ſaying: thys man is worthye to dye: for he hathe propheſyed agaynſt this Citie / as yee haue heard with your eares. Then ſpake Ieremiah vnto all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / and to the people / ſaying: The Lorde hathe ſent me to propheſie againſt this houſe / and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte this Citie / all the things that yee haue heard. Therfore nowe amend your wayes and workes / and heare the voyce of the Lorde your God / that the Lorde maye repent hym of the plague that he hathe pronounced agaynſte you. As for me / beholde / I am in your handes: doe wyth me as you thinke good and ryghte. But knowe yee for certaine / that if you putte mee to deathe / yee ſhall ſurely bring innocent bloud vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelues / and vpon thys Citie / and vpon the inhabitants therof: for of a truthe the Lorde hath ſent me vnto you / to ſpeake all theſe words in your cares.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11227:2"/>
            <head>To the godly readers</head>
            <head type="sub">Grace and peace from God. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe treatyſe enſuing (Chriſtian Reader) being in dede purpoſely meant / as the tytle pretendeth / to be a ſeconde Admonition to the Parliament / as yet not being not diſſolued / cannot chuſe I am ſure / but be read of diuers / that are not of that honourable aſſembly at thys tyme / ſo that though the treatiſe is principally directed to them / yet the knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matters / as it muſt needes paſſe further / ſo are they<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>own / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tonly</note> neceſſary to be further known / and they are the liker to take good effect / by meanes of the general conſent of thoſe that like them / and eſpecially by meanes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythful prayers / whych many good men ſhall poure forthe to God for hys gracious good bleſſyng therin: wherfore ſome thyng was to be ſayd in a Preface / as me thought / which might be direc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to thee (chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian reader) whoſoeuer thou art / that lighteſt vpon thys boke to read it. And world to God many moe myght read thys boke then are lyke / bycauſe muche worſe will be ſayd againſt it / by them whych ſhall ſpeake of it by heare ſay / then could / or would be ſaid / <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th muche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt.</note> if all read it that will ſpeake of it: whereof we haue had too much experience in the former Admonition. But we haue caſt our accompts whych do bend our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to deale in theſe matters / not onely to abyde hard wordes / but hard and ſharpe dealings alſo for our laboure / and yet ſhall we thynke oure laboure w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll beſtowed / it by God hys grace / we attayne but to thus much / to giue ſome light of that reformation of religion whych is grounded vpon Gods boke / and<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yne / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is &amp; ſuche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bokes.</note> ſomewhat to haue opened the deformities of oure Engliſh reformation / whych hyghly diſpleaſeth our eternall God. Neuertheleſſe / if it might be / we wold be ſory to offend any / but eſpecially any good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man / for our purpoſe is not / if we may chuſe / to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urchaſe more hatred / or get vs more enenmies / for
<pb facs="tcp:11227:2"/> vndeſerued we haue of that / and them far too much<note place="margin">We haue too many enemies / too much hatred al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued.</note> already / and to offend the godly man / is farre from our meaning / for God knoweth we altogether ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke to do ſuch good. But what is ther in our bokes that ſhould offend any that be / or would ſeeme to be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd yet ſome man may ſay either there is muche amiſſe in our bokes / or elſe we haue a great deale of wrong offered vs / and that by ſuche men as woulde ſeeme to be the fathers of all true godlyneſſe / for the authors of the former haue bene &amp; are hardly hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">Next doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging</note> / to be ſent cloſe pryſoners to Newgate / next dore to hangyng / and by ſome of no meane eſtimation it hath bene ſayd (as is reported) that it had bene well for them / if they had beene ſente to Bedlem to ſaue<note place="margin">Bedlem.</note> their lyues / as though they had bene in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earill of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hanged / and another lykely prelate ſayde / if they were at hys orderyng / Newgate ſhould haue beene<note place="margin">Newgat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their ſuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and fette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> their ſure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e / and fetters their bondes. And yet now that they haue had the law / and I thynke wyth the moſt too / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they were cloſe priſoners / they are found nether to haue ben traytors nor rebels / and if it had bent tryed by Gods law / they ſhould not haue beene<note place="margin">The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> former ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monition no rebels our lawe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by Gods lawe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ers. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> former ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion</note> found to haue offended agaynſt that lawe at all / but to haue deſerued prayſe of that lawe / and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of God / as ryghtly that learned man mayſter Beza ſayth they deſerue / which oppoſe themſelues againſt ſuch endeuours / as they doe in that little booke / farre worſe then thoſe / whych he calleth a manifeſt falling away from Chriſt. And I pray the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gentle Reader marke theſe words wel of that great learned &amp; godly M. Beza / and it ſhall anſwer for them to two men / principally / that haue erneſtly declamed againſt that admonition / and the authors therof. The one ſayd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t was a folyſhe boke: the other ſayd the authors were to raſhe in ſetting it forth wythout a councell / and I wot not what allowance before it wer de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ed. But thys learned man anſwereth them bothe wyth one word / that it is a commendable work / and deſerueth no diſprayſe. And whatſoeuer the declaimer ſaythe / 
<pb facs="tcp:11227:3"/> they ſhalbe circumſpect enough / that ſhall auouche vndoubted truthes out of the ſcriptures though they wait not for the conſent of a fewe / no nor yet of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icenſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s non re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch like li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes vſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs vs / a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t fallyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hriſte.</note> / for maiſter Beza dare ſay / it is a manifeſt falling away from Chriſte to maintaine pluralities of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices / licences for non reſidence. &amp;c. though he heare not that any cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel hath agreed vpon it in England / ſor he knoweth it is a reſolued truth in all ryght re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed churches / and eſpecially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. And what I pray you haue they done amiſſe / but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamer alſo offended in it / if it be an offence? They haue publiſhed in Print that the miniſterie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is out of ſquare / &amp; he hath publiſhed at Paules croſſe / that the biſhops of England haue bene vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in making of miniſters / and that hathe he publyſhed before any councell in England had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te hym <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe.</note> it. Woulde to God he had neuer done worſe faulte / nay / woulde he had not more offended there / whych he craued pardone for / when he had done it / and yet ſo / as he ſayd he cared not thoughe they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned hym not / for he thinketh of lyke / that he neede not care for offending the poore members of Ieſus Chriſt / and for as muche as he ſpake agaynſte them two in Newgate / he ſhall neuer goe to Newgate for ſaying the byſhops were vncircumſpect. I coulde wiſhe ſuch to be more circumſpect what they ſaye to offend ſimple / and pore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſte. Let ſuch men remember the penaltie threatned / better a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 18.</note> tied about their necks / and they drowned in the depth of the ſea. Nowe I neede not aſke what they haue aunſwered to that boke / for they haue anſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auiſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lke.</note> nothyng / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is a folyſh booke. &amp;c / but wyth godly wyſe men I truſt / that will not be taken for a ſufficient anſwere / as in deede it is not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They ſaye there is an anſwere towards / for my part I long to<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n anſwer wardes.</note> ſee it / and yet to ſay truthe / I ſhould be lothe / conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering they cannot but betray their weakneſſe to the papiſtes / or elſe confirme them in their follyes / but principally offend the churche of God. And in parte / 
<pb facs="tcp:11227:3"/> you ſhall perceiue their dealing / in a collection that they haue made of thoſe things which they miſſelike<note place="margin">what the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dealyng will be / is to be ſeen by that which the haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in thys.</note> in the former Admonition / by a ſhort treatiſe contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a confutation of their collection or view as they call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. The treatiſe came to oure handes / the author vnknowne / and we haue thought good to unparte it to thee (Chriſtian reader) that thou mighteſt ſee and conſider. But what ſtand I ſo much in defence of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> former admonition. Some peraduenture wil thinke I had nede to ſpeake for thys ſecond more. But till I heare more / I will ſay little. Yet thus muche I ſay / if ſome ſuppoſe it to be too particular / &amp; to touch the quicke to neare / let them thynke withall how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary it is to be knowne / and further / that theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities<note place="margin">Poyntes to be thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght of.</note> be the cauſe that we require reformation / and what an intollerable thing it is to ſuffer all theſe enormities amongſt vs. And if ſome doute whether all the particulares be true that are heere named / let them ſeeke examination / and they ſhall fynde farre<note place="margin">Seke exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination.</note> worſe matter / then is here alleaged. They ſhal finde ſuch ſtomacke of one ſide againſt the other / that they cannot abide any thyng / neuer ſo wel done of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide / and that of a ſtomacke. I will not open an olde<note place="margin">ſtomacke.</note> vlcer / or examine whye the Geneua tranſlation and notes of the Bible fynde ſo little fauoure / althoughe<note place="margin">Geneua Bible.</note> to thys day no tranſlation is ſo good in England. I will not rip vp among our prelates the ſymonie / the treacherie ſo particularly as is come to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. But thoſe particulars which I haue touched / the very occaſion forced me to it / and ſuche iuſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I may haue / that I maye be more particulare hereafter. Now / whereas ſome very vnproperly (as<note place="margin">Vnprope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> applying of Cham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> examyle. Gen. 9.</note> I thinke) do ſay that we in thys do vncouer our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers priuities / and would withe vs to forbeare ſo to do. We are of their minde that Cham dyd noughte / but they ſhall not fynde vs like that ribaulde Cham / which toke delite in that nakedneſſe / they ſhall finde the time ſeruers / and ſuch as dallye wyth the ſhame<note place="margin">Cham a ribaulde.</note> of nakedneſſe in thys time / they ſhall fynde them to
<pb facs="tcp:11227:4"/> take Chams trade / but for vs / we woulde / and doe<note place="margin">Time ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers take Chams <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rade. Gen. 9. 23.</note> what we can / to couer thys ſhame with a ryght co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer / that is with a right reformation / and that do we going backward / as men lothe and ſorye to heare of the nakedneſſe / and deſirous to couer it / that our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (if they wil be our fathers) may no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſhew their ſhame. Againe wheras ſome men (&amp; that good men to) wil ſay theſe treatiſes be too hotte for thys<note place="margin">Theſe tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes to hot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r thys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me / aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>weared. Gods mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e minſed. Eſay. 58. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> time / I wiſh to know wherin? whether in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters whych we handle? or in the handlyng of the matters? The matters are Gods / wherin we may not minſe hym. And the deformities haue continued long / and are manifeſtly intollerable / where againſt we are commaunded to cry out. Crye out and ceaſe not / lift vp thy voice lyke a trumpet / &amp; tell my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple their wickedneſſe / and the houſe of Iacob their ſynnes / ſayth the Lord to hys Prophet / whych ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verſe folowing / doth ſo belong to vs / that we ſhall hardly anſwer it to God / if we doe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary / &amp; ſcarſe wel anſwere it / that we haue forborne ſo long. And who they be / and what the ſcrypture thinketh of them / that require that their Preachers<note place="margin">Eſay. 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al. 1. 10. Exod. 32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. reg. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. 27. Math. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cor. 5. 13. Ih. 9. 10 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 15 &amp; 23 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atter / and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to ſerue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction.</note> ſhould ſpeake pleaſing things / it is more euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then that I neede to amplifie that point. Againe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which ſtudie and endeuor to pleaſe men / are not the ſeruaunts of God / Paules wordes are plaine. Now for the handling of the matters / whereas ſome will ſay ſuch a ſentence is too hote / and ſuche and ſuche a worde is too ſharpe / if they meaſure oure zeale with the zeale of milde Moiſes / of Elias / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets / of Iohn Baptiſt / of Paul / of the Apoſtles / of Iohn the elder againſt Diotrephes / of Chriſt our ſauiour agaynſt the Phariſeis / I truſt they ſhall finde vs to kepe our ſelues wythin the bounds of the examples of the ſcriptures. And if they marke oure wrytings well / they ſhal finde vs to haue vttered nothing but true / and neceſſary matter / and to haue framed oure words vnto our matter / &amp; not to haue ſought words to ſerue our affections. But they whych ſpeake ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly
<pb facs="tcp:11227:4"/> of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offend not / o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their doing / which call them rebels and ſeditious / which are faithfull ſubiects to God &amp; their Prince / which eyther wreſt mennes words / or falſefie them / what deſerue they? God forgiue them that / and far worſe matters / for his Chriſtes ſake / and giue them better mindes towardes hys true churche &amp; a ryght reformation. And yet for as much as we heare they will anſwere vs / thys I ſay / if they wil keepe them to the truth it ſelfe / the worde of God / then wyll the<note place="margin">Ioh. 17. 17 A good iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue where matters of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / are tried by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worde of God it ſelf. A craft of the papiſts to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhew of au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie.</note> maters ſhortly come to a good iſſue / but if they draw vs to other trials / there will proue craft in dawbing (as they ſay) for that hath beene the craft of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes / to rigge vp all corners / and to fynde all the ſhiftes they can / to haue ſcope enough to varie a lye: to ſay much nothing to the profe / and yet to amaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people wyth ſhewe of authorities. But if they will anſwer vs ſtill wyth crueltie &amp; perſecution / we will kepe our ſelues out of their handes / as long as God ſhall giue vs leaue / and content our ſelues wyth pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience / if God ſuffer vs to fall into their handes / and ſurely we ſhall hardly eſcape them / if they and their doers which be certaine perſecuting printers / maye haue their willes. And heere humbly we beſeche her maieſtie / not to be ſtirred agaynſt vs / by ſuch men as<note place="margin">An humb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> requeſt to her m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> will endeuoure to bring vs more into hatred / which will not care what to lay to our charge / ſo they may oppreſſe vs / and ſuppreſſe the truth: They will ſaye we deſpiſe authoritie / and ſpeake againſte her ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignetie. But O Lord what will not enuie ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">Ill wil n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſayde well.</note> truth? ill will (they ſay) neuer ſayd well. No / no / we heartely / plainly and faythfully profeſſe / that the chefe gouernors in ciuill matters / haue chefe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ouer all perſons / in their dominions &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys<note place="margin">Rom. 13. Eſ. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. chr. 19. 5. 6. 7. 8.</note> / and are the ſofter fathers / and nurſſes of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes church. And as Iehoſaphat hauing cheefe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie / did by his authoritie ſet vp / and defend not only the ciuill gouernment / but alſo the true refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the church at that time / in hys dominion / 
<pb facs="tcp:11227:5"/> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 2. 3. 4.</note> to our ſoueraigne / beſeeching her Maieſtie / and the whole ſtate / to proceede in it. And thys is moſt true / that her Maieſtie ſhall not finde better ſubiectes in her land / then thoſe that deſire a righte reformation / <note place="margin">Moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes.</note> whoſe goodes / bodyes / and lyues / are moſte aſſured to her Maieſtie / and to their Countrey / and which ceaſe not to poure forthe their heartie prayers vnto God for her maieſties long &amp; happy raigne in muche proſperitie / to be an auncient matrone in Iſraell / in the church of God in England / and her dominions / to defend and maintaine the ſame in much peace and godlyneſſe / al the dayes of her maieſties natural life / and to be crowned after in heauen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eternall glory / whych I beſeche God by the working of his ſpirit / fully to accompliſhe and performe for hys Chriſtes ſake: which thing alſo (Chriſtian reader) I beſeeche thee to commend vnto God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually in thy earneſt prayer. And thus for thys time / deſiring thee to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſe thys treatiſe wyth a ſingle eye / as alſo I deſire<note place="margin">A ſingle eye.</note> all thoſe that are of the honourable aſſemblye of the Parliament to doe / for the time that the parliament continueth proroged / that they may be wel acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the matters when they come together againe: I doe commend you and them / and continually will commend you bothe / in my earneſt prayers vnto our good / and gracious Lord god / to whom in Trinitie of perſons / and vnitie of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head / be aſcribed / and geuen al au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie / dominion / and power for euer. So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11227:5"/>
            <head>¶ A SECONDE admonition to the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is no new matter to ſee the faithfull and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable admonitions of God his preachers cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhly reiected of them / which ſhould gladly and thankfully heare and embrace them / which ſhould obay them / which ſhould to their vttermoſte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote them / which ſhould employ themſelues to defend them: and yet it is as olde a cuſtome as it is lamentable / to finde ſuch as ſhuld be moſt frends / moſt foes. To leaue the eldeſt times / when *<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 4. 8.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel found no worſſe freende then Came / his owne brother / when Iſmael *<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 4. 29.</note> perſecuted Iſaac / when Eſau *<note n="c" place="margin">Ge. 27. 41.</note> Iacob / when Ioſeph *<note n="d" place="margin">Ge. 37. 23.</note> was perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his owne brethren / when Moſes *<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 12. 13. 14.</note> was fame to flee from Egipte bicauſe of the Iewes / and ſo forthe till the time of the Prophetes / when *<note n="f" place="margin">Iere. 26. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Ieremie found leaſt fauor at the prieſts hands / when Ozeah ſaythe that Gilead the *<note n="g" place="margin">Oſe. 6. 8.</note> colledge of prieſtes was a citie of wicked doers / and polluted with bloud / when Amos was ſo ill entreated by *<note n="h" place="margin">Am. 7. 10.</note> Amazia the prieſt of Bethel / yea leauing theſe / and comming nearer / when our ſauioure Chriſte crieth *<note n="i" place="margin">Math. 23. 13. 14. &amp;c.</note> woe to the Scribes and Phariſeis / exact intexpreters of God his lawe / bicauſe of their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie / who though they would faine ſeeme ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / yet had they not the heartes to yeelde to the truth preached by oure ſauioure / bicauſe their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite
<pb facs="tcp:11227:6"/> and gaine (as they thought) lay another way: they therfore yeelded not / but in ſteede therof they ſlaundered Chriſtes perſon / and his doctrine / they bent themſelues wholely againſt hym / they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted hym / yea the texte is plaine / that Phariſeis and prieſtes all of them / *<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 11. 47</note> counſelled againſte hym / lefte him not till they broughte him to hys death / nay which is more / one of his owne compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / one of the principall / one of the *<note n="l" place="margin">mat. 26. 48</note> twelue / Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das letrayed him. Lette vs caſte oure eyes vppon the Apoſtles / they founde not onely the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis &amp; prieſtes theyr maſters cheefe perſecutors / to be theirs alſo / but diuers *<note n="m" place="margin">2. Corinth. 11. 26.</note> falſe brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / I ſay brethren / but falſe brethren / neuertheles they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and were taken for brethren / theſe I ſaye they were endanngered by: ſo then / to ouerpaſſe the examples of the church ſince / as they are reported in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories (bicauſe we haue and may haue euer beſt lighte by the ſcriptures) this is it I wold ſay / that in theſe our dayes / the preachers finde not leſſe fauoure / nay they are not more ſlaundered and perſecuted / by any / then not onely by the learned of the popiſhe profeſſyon / but alſo by ſuche as woulde ſeeme pillers of the true religion. And ſurely a ſtraunge thing it is / and a maruellous caſe / and muche to the diſmay of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that it ſhould be ſo / ſauing that in peruſing the ſcriptures / it is found to haue beene commonly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. There were two little Treatiſes lately ſette forthe / both tending to one ende / namely to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe the parliament / what it had to doe touching religion / and tending to one ende / they beare one name / that is / an Admonition to the parliament. The matters therin contained / howe true ſo euer they be / haue founde ſmall fauoure. The perſones that are thoughte to haue made them / are laide in no worſſe priſon then Newgate. The men that ſette vpon them / are no worſſe men the Biſhops.
<pb facs="tcp:11227:6"/> The name that goeth of them / is no better then rebelles / and great woordes there are / that theyr daunger will yet proue greater: well / whatſoeuer is ſaid / or done againſt them / or whoſoeuer ſpeake or worke againſt them / that is not the matter: but the equitie of their cauſe is the matter. And yet this I will ſay / that the ſtate ſheweth not it ſelfe vpright / if it ſuffer them ſo to be moleſted / for that which was ſpoken only in the way of admonition to the parliament / which / was to conſider of anye ſuche admonition / and to receiue it or reiecte it / without further matter to the Authors: except it contained ſome wilfull maintenaunce of manyfeſt rebellion / or treaſon / which it cannot be proued to doe. Againe appealing as they doe to that hygheſt Court of Parliament / from the lower of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops / and Commiſſioners / bicauſe they finde not equitie at their handes / nor cannot / the Biſhops / who are in their Admonition moſt touched / being cheefeſt in Commiſſion / alledge the Parliament what it will (as ſome ſay it was not in fourme of lawe / and Imprinted / and yet I trowe there may be founde preſidentes of the like / as that of Rode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike Mors / the way to Common wealthe / the Complaint of the beggers / and ſuch like.) All ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men ſhall finde lacke of equitie / if their ſafetie be not prouided for in this reſpecte / yea / and their appeale thought vppon / heard / and yeelded vnto. If it were the caſe of any number / for worldly reſpectes / this high Courte were to prouide for it / but being the caſe of the whole church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande / and Irelande / and in deede God his cauſe / all good conſciences ſhall condemne that Courte / that prouideth not for it / but reiecteth it. The ſcripture is plaine / it *<note n="n" place="margin">Math. 10. 14. 15.</note> ſhall be eaſyer for So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Gomorrha in the day of iudgement / then for ſuch a Court. God giue it grace to prouide for it / or euer it be diſſolued / and pardon the neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:11227:7"/> already committed / for otherwiſe ſurely / there is none other thyng to be loked for / then ſome ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die vengeance to lyght vpon the whole land / pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide as well as the politique Macheuils of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande thinke they can / though God do his worſte: but ſhut God out of your aſſemblies and courtes / as hetherto in this youre laſte Parliament you haue don nothing therin as you ought / no though you haue bene ſolicited / but haue ſuffred them that were your ſolicitoures / to be moleſted / you ſhall finde / bothe that you oughte to haue ſoughte the *<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 6. 33</note> kingdome of God firſt / and alſo you ſhal finde / if you conſider not youre owne wayes in youre heartes / howe you thinke it a time to builde ſeeled houſes / to deuiſe lawes for the preſeruation and proſperitie of your common wealth / and neglecte God his churche / leaue that waſte / prouide not for that / you ſhall finde (as the *<note n="p" place="margin">Ag. 1. 5. 6.</note> Prophet ſaith) yee ſhall ſowe muche / and bring in little / yee ſhall eate / and not haue inoughe. As for the Conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion houſe / whereof many haue conceiued a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous opinion / and which ſhould of duetie loke to theſe matters / common experience dothe proue / that they doe for the moſt parte apply them ſelues to the time / and ſeeke rather to pleaſe and followe worldly pollicie / then ſincerely to promote Gods cauſe / and to publiſhe his truth. And hereof their laſt conuocations can be good witneſſes. But you ſay the Biſhops are good men / &amp; great clearkes / they knowe what they haue to doe / and poſſyble ſome of them doe / excepte the God of thys worlde haue bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded their eyes / and ſo did ſome of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe biſhops: but you were deceiued by them / and you are like to be deceiued by theſe / if you truſte them ſo farre / as experience teacheth. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you ſhall die in *<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ze. 33. 8.</note> your ſynnes / you ſhal both *<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 15. 14</note> fall into the ditche. But ſome will ſay that the admonition hindered other things. As who ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:11227:7"/> ſay that to further Gods cauſe / is to hinder other matters that be profitable for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth / doth the knowledge of God / and the promoting of hys glory / hinder profitable lawes? that is a thyng that I would gladly learne / for I coulde neuer vnderſtand it before. VVherfore this may be as a ſeconde Admonition / wyth the like mynde as afore by them / to craue redreſſe of the great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes in oure Reformation of Religion / ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continued from the papiſtes / ſome deuiſed by the fantaſticall heades of vayne menne / and ſome though not maintayned / yet ſuffered and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed vnto thys day / yea and further / as they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / doe againe appeale to thys hyghe Courte of Parliament from all other Courtes / being ready to defende that whych I wryte touching the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it againſte all men / and that vppon the pearill of my lyfe. Let me be but vprightly heard and interpreated. The matter is Goddes / ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe it not lightly / for we maye not (thoughe you deuiſed lawes to cutte vs off / as by ſome one by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop you haue bene ere nowe prouoked) for oure partes thus leaue it. The other bokes are ſhorte (as it was requiſite to preſent to you) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue not ſo muche tolde you how to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme / as what to Reforme. They haue tolde you of many things amiſſe / and that very truely / they haue tolde you in generall / what were to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red / but howe to doe theſe things / as it is the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt poynte / ſo it requireth / as themſelues ſaye / a larger diſcourſe. I meane therfore to ſupplie (as ſhortly as I can / bicauſe I wryte as they dyd to you) ſome thing that may make to the expreſſing of the matter / ſo plainely / that you may haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient lyght to proceede by / till they whych are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued wyth greater giftes / diſcuſſe it more exactly / or till we our ſelues / who haue begon / maye haue further oportunitie to proceede / if it be neglected of
<pb facs="tcp:11227:8"/> theyr part which coulde we it better. And yet this I dare ſay / for the ſubſtance of thoſe Treatiſes (which is it that galleth the aduerſaries mooſte / howe ſo euer they quarrell w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them vpon wordes) that it is ſo grounded vpon the vndoubted truthe of God his booke / that the diuell of hell / cannot wyth his coloures blemiſhe it / ſaue he may ſeeke to ſuppreſſe it by violence: nor any but he / and thoſe whome he hathe deceiued / or whome God hath not yet giuen ſo much light vnto / will or can ſtand againſt it. I would / and doe therefore ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly admoniſhe them that knowe / to knowe as they ought / and to doe as they knowe / and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the <note n="*" place="margin">vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this of the deuill / as Ioh. 12. 31 Ih. 14. 30. Ephe. 6. 12 2. Cor. 44. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. 2. 3 Rom. 10. 2</note> God of this worlde / that he deceiue them not / for the time will come / that this * dung ſhall be throwne openly in their faces / to their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ſhame / that maintain it / like as at this day it hathe befallen to the ſenceleſse Papiſtes / who will neuer giue ouer / til they can neither wil nor chuſe with ſhame inough. Next I woulde / and doe earneſtly ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oniſhe thoſe that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant / to learne to knowe / and to beware of a blinde zeale / which is more violent &amp; vniuſt / then oughte elſe / carying men headlong / to maintain that / they haue no reaſon for / and wickedly to gainſtand the expreſſe truth / to their endleſſe perdition. Now to the matter / I ſay that we are ſo ſkarce come to the outwarde face of a Churche rightly refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med / that although ſome truth be taught by ſome preachers / yet no preacher may withoute greate danger of the lawes / vtter all truthe compriſed in the booke of God. It is ſo circumſcribed &amp; wrapt within the compaſſe of ſuche ſtatutes / ſuche pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties / ſuche inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uctions / ſuche aduertiſements / ſuche articles / ſuche canons / ſuche ſober caueats / and ſuche manifo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e pamphlets / that in manner it doth but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>epe out from beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de the ſcreene. The lawes of the lande / the booke of common prayer / 
<pb facs="tcp:11227:8"/> the Queenes Iniunctions / the Commiſſioners aduertiſements / the biſhops late Canons / Lind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woodes Proumetais / euery biſhops Articles in his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oceſſe / my Lord of Canterburies ſober caue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates / in his licences to preachers / and hys highe Courte of prerogatiue or graue fatherly faculties / theſe together / or the worſte of them (as ſome of them be too badde) may not be broken or offended againſt / but with more daunger then to offende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Bible. To theſe ſubſcribing / and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ing againe / and the third ſubſcribing / are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>red / for theſe / Preachers and others are endi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are fined / are priſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned / are excommunicated / are baniſhed / and haue worſe things threatned them: and the Bible / that muſte haue no further ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pe / then by theſe it is aſſigned. Is this to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe God his worde? is this are formation? He that could not abide ſtraunge fire in the olde law / but burnt *<note n="ſ" place="margin">Leui. 10. 12</note> them that vſed it / what will he doe to vs in the newe lawe / that erect a new and ſtraunge courſe / or worde / to rule his church by? What did the Pope but ſo? he did ſuffer God his worde to haue a courſe as farre as it pleaſed him / ſo that he might haue the whole authoritie aboue it. ſo dyd the Popiſhe churche: but we ſay the * worde is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue<note place="margin">Ephe. 2. 20</note> the church / then ſurely it is aboue the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe churche / and aboue all theſe bookes afore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. If it be ſo / why are not they ouer ruled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> / and not it by them? Here falleth forthe to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſwered a ſhift of deſcant to turne and winde this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>er. Forſothe theſe are not repugnant / ſaythe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the woorde of God / no nor yet ſay we / are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſonante / no more is chaffe like to quenche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no nor yet can it abide the fire. But gold can. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uen ſo are theſe vnable to quenche the lighte of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> goſpell / no *<note n="t" place="margin">1 Corrin. 3.</note> nor yet can they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> abide the courte o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the goſpell / but true religion abideth the triall of the word of God. As wel reaſoned / it were to ſay / 
<pb facs="tcp:11227:9"/> lay hay or ſtubble on the fire / for it wil not quench the fire / and therefore it will not be conſumed by the fire / as to ſay receiue this reformation / for it is not repugnant / therefore it will abide the triall of the word / but the ſcripture abideth no ſuche di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of contrary / and diuers / for he that is not with me / take he the Iewes parte / the Turkes / the Papiſtes / or the hipocriticall Engliſhe prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes parte / * <note n="v" place="margin">Mat. 12 30</note> he is againſt me ſayth Chriſte. Another / he talketh for the Quenes ſupremacie / Out ſaythe he / may not the Queene doe thys and that / but you muſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>her to a reckening: howe allowe you then hir ſupremacie in Eccleſiaſticall things / (which are in deede to be determined in conferences and councels / and that by the warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the worde) you will proue very Anabaptiſtes / not ſuffering Magiſtrates / nor any politique or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders beſides / and ſo he runneth away with allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſcriptures that commaunde obedience to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates / and ſay things muſt be done orderly and decently / and he deuiſeth many foule names / and reproches for vs. But heere hir Maieſtie is to be humbly intreated / that of hir clemencie / ſhee will abide vs (who are bound by duetie / and obedience to God) freely to diſcuſſe all things as they are ſet <note n="*" place="margin">Deu. 4. 4 Ioſ. 1. 8.</note> forthe in the woorde of God / though her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie otherwiſe thinke it ſtraunge / and alſo haue in owe to exaſperate hir Maieſtie againſt vs pore men / who are farre vnable to abide hit diſpleſure / and would be ſory to offende her / if it might pleaſe God to encline her Maieſties heart to conſider of our cauſe / and not to be turned from vs by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunateneſſe of oure aduerſaries / nor by other preiudice of oure perſones or places: but to deale with vs euen according to the truthe of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters we deale in / which are according to the very woorde of almightie God / or elſe if it will not fall out ſo / we will be content to abide hir diſpleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:11227:9"/> and ſharp puniſhment. Out if it fal out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o / then as an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>oure Magiſtrate may not take the authoritie of the higheſt into hys hantes / no more may any Magiſtrate v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urpe Gods. To Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Math. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21.</note> geue that whych is Ceſars / &amp; to God that whych is hys / ſaythe oure ſauioure. Non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſo high at her common wealthe / as hir maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: none ſo vſe the ſweard but ſhee / and whom ſhee appointeth vnder hir / according to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lawes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> of thys land / ſo that it be not repugnant to their vocation / as to miniſters. Likewyſe / none is ſo hygh in the churche as Chriſte / none to doe any thing / nor any thing to be done in hys churche / but as it is appointed in hys woorde / eyther by preciſe or generall direction. And therfore it is allowed and commaunded to Chriſtian men / to trie all <note n="y" place="margin">1. Th. 5 / 21</note> * things / and to holde that whiche is good / whoſoeuer forb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dde wythoute exception / Prince / or other / ſo that if we examine euerye thyng done in thys churche of God in Englande <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> by the worde of God / and holde that whiche is good / though the lawe be offended / that lawe is to be reformed / and not we to be puniſhed / for whatſoeuer our perſonnes or places be / if oure matters we deale in / be Gods / her maieſtie we truſt / remembreth what the ſcripture ſayth: he that deſpiſeth you * <note n="z" place="margin">Lu. 10 / 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> deſpiſeth me / and he that receyueth you / receyueth me. As we know thys caſe to be cleare / ſo we truſt and dayly pray / that God wyll open her maieſties heart / to conſider of it and vs. But to theſe men agayne / let them ſhewe vs (if they can) by what aucthoritie they may en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyne vs (if God hys worde beare them to be magiſtrates) to obſerue the boke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<note place="margin">More ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / then we ſay for the Bible.</note> prayers / bothe in matter and manner / as in theyr laſte Canons they forbid theyr miniſters to depart from one or other? it is wycked to ſay no worſe of it / ſo to attribute to a booke / in deede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulled out of the vile popiſh ſeruice booke / with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11227:10"/> ſome certaine rubrikes and gloſes of their owne deuiſe / ſuche authoritie as only is due to God hys booke: and inditements / impriſonments / and ſuche extremities vſed agaynſt them which breake it / is cruell perſecution of the members<note place="margin">Cruel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</note> of Ieſus Chriſte. And of all other greeuous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities layde vppon thys churche of God in England / this is the greateſt / that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to vtter that whych we learne truely oute of the ſcriptures. We muſt be in daunger of a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> premunire if we folowe not the lawes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land / thoughe they be agaynſte the ſcriptures / and in daunger of a twelue monthes impriſoment / if we ſpeake agaynſt the booke of common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er / though it be agaynſte the word of God. In deede if there were order taken for conferences / <note place="margin">Acts. 15. 2</note> ſuch as the ſcriptures commendeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church for the triall of truthe / when it is hard &amp; darke / then were the dealing not harde / but vprighte. As for the Conuocation houſe I tolde you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> what it was / and what may be looked for at theyr handes / and ſomewhat more ſhall be ſayde of it heereafter. If that were ſayd for the Bible / whych is ſayd for the booke of common prayer / and whych God ſayth in his law for hys <note n="*&amp;" place="margin">Deut. 4. 2</note> woorde / then were the dealyng vpryght and and good. Now if they meane by / not repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that it is conſonante in all and euerye the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof wyth the woorde of God / that can they neuer proue. But coulde they proue that / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> yet they ſnare the church of God betweene that boke and other bookes / whych they obtrude w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtraight charge to be obſerued / whych bookes doe differ amongs themſelues: as the booke of common prayer / and the iniunctions about wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers / the boke of common prayer and the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements about the churche veſtures / the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons againſt the pontificall / in not ordering of miniſters / ſine titulo, the preface of the laſt boke
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11227:10"/> of homilies / and of the laſt newe Bible agaynſt the booke of Common prayer in the manner of reading of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. And in many things the biſhops articles in theyr ſeuerall dioceſſes differ from thys booke / as aboute the ſtandyng of the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> table / &amp; fetchyng the dead to church / and ſuch lyke / but the courte of Faculties / that<note place="margin">Thus ſhal they be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plexed / that follow me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s heades.</note> for marrying wythoute aſking the banes / and many moe things differeth from it and all other theyr bookes / but cheefely from God hys Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> what ſay we to thys caſe? we are neyther free to folowe the Bible / nor out of doubt what to doe by theſe bookes / but to followe God and hys woorde / we are ſo free / that we are by the Apoſtle forbidden to become ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts <note n="*a" place="margin">1. Cor. 7 / 23</note> of men. If thys be true / as who can denye it / then is it your partes to rid our churche of theſe ſhrewde encombrances. And whereas it was meant to bridle papiſts / make direct lawes againſt them.<note place="margin">Directe lawes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes.</note> Further / wheras our church yet miſſeth of the right courſe of the ſcriptures in our reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / let youre learned men be driuen to drawe a plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme out of God his boke (wher it is deſcrybed at ful) according to hys will in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame reuealed / and the examples of the beſt Churches beyonde the ſeas / as Geneua / Fraunce / &amp;c. And the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">The cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> agree.</note> cauſe why our church differeth from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches reformed of the ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers / or amongs our ſelues / or they amongs themſelues / is becauſe one church ſuffereth not it ſelfe ſo to be directed by the courſe of the ſcriptures as an other doth / except it be in thoſe things of order / wherin one pariſhe may many times differ from an other<note place="margin">Churches may differ in matters of order.</note> wythout offence / folowing the generall rules of the ſcripture for order / as in appoynting tyme and place for prayers / and ſo forth. So that we are ſo farre off from ſingularitie wherwyth we are commonly charged / that we deſire to drawe by one line with the primitiue churche / and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11227:11"/> churches beſt reformed at thys day / for we ſay there is but one * <note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 3. 16</note> line throughout all cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis / and at all times as the ſcripture ſpeaketh / there is one * <note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 4. 4.</note> body / one ſpirite / one hope / one Lorde / one fayth / one baptiſme / one God and Father of all which is aboue all / and through al / and in vs all. The perſons and cauſes that are to deale and to be dealt with in the church are certayne / and expreſſed in the ſcriptures. The lyfe of the worde is the miniſterie of the ſame / howe ſhall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> they heare wythout a *<note n="d" place="margin">Ro. 10. 14</note> preacher ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. The former tretiſes therfore haue right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken againſt the baſtard / idol / and vnprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching miniſterie of thys church. And therefore thys I ſay / that firſt you muſt prouide a ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient<note place="margin">Sufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rouiſyon for the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſteric.</note> mayntenance for the miniſterie / that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery pariſhe they may haue a preaching paſtor / one or moe / that may only entend that charge. Is not the ſcripture plaine: Thou ſhalt not *<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 9. 9. 10. 11. 12. &amp;c. Deu. 25. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ti. 5. 18 Ro. 15. 27. Deu. 18. 1</note> mouſel the mouth of the Oxe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that treadeth out <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> the corne? for our ſakes no doubt thys is wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten / that he that careth ſhould care in hope / that they whych ſowe you ſpirituall things / myght reape of you temporall things / whych is no bad exchaunge for you. Nowe / to your handes oure aunceſtors haue raiſed a maintenance / which is not ſo embeſeled away / nor the propertie ſo alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red / but that (though mennes deuotion be colde to the miniſters) the ſtate may eaſely by law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> the ſame prouiſion againe / without loſſe in manner to any partie. If none other way may be founde / then haue the biſhops and cathedrall churches temporalties inough / to redeme thoſe liuings that be impropriated / or otherwyſe out / and to better thoſe liuings whych are too ſmall / and as I thynke to be employed to other good vſes of the church alſo. But we will not ſtande wyth you ſo muche in the manner of the raiſyng of theyr prouiſion / for raiſe it as it ſhall pleaſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11227:11"/> God to put you in minde / ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> you prouide ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently for your miniſters / that they maye be of abilitie to maintaine their charge / and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe vpon fitte furniture of bokes and honeſt hoſpitalitie. But in the meane while / vntill a ſufficient prouiſion be made / it is no better then ſacrileage and ſpoyling of God to kepe backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way the prouiſion which hath bene made in that reſpecte / and the curſſe of God threatned by Malachie to thoſe that ſpoiled y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> *<note n="f" place="margin">mal. 3. 8. 9</note> Leuites then of their prouiſion / belongeth / and wil light vpon our ſpoilers nowe / &amp; vpon them in whoſe hands it is to redreſſe it / if they doe it not. Alſo there muſt be orders taken and looked vnto / for<note place="margin">beſtowing of vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity liuings</note> the beſtowing of the liuings prouided in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſities (now dennes of many theeuiſh non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſidentes:) not to the greedy vſe of many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morant maſters of colledges / and at theyr wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked pleaſure / as they are / but to the brynging vp for the moſte parte of ſuch as wil be content to be employed vpon the charge of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the church ſhall haue nede of them / and to take from them that haue moe liuings / all ſaue one / and that to / except they will be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent / and be able and willyng to diſcharge it / hauing beſides the allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which afterwards ſhalbe ſpoken of by God hys grace. And thys prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt ſo ſufficiently be eſtabliſhed / that it may be paide wythoute adoe / and not to be<note place="margin">mat. 10. 17 2. cor. 2 67 Miniſters maintna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is not to be recouered by exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. Vnburde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices.</note> ſought for / or worme by ſuſpenſions / or * excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> / which are applied by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcriptures to a farre more proper and ſpirituall vſe / &amp; not at all to thys. And alſo there are many charges going out of benefices / wherof they ſhoulde be vnburdened. Next / you muſt repeale your ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or ſtatutes / whereby you haue authoriſed that miniſterie that now is / making your eſtate partly to conſiſt of Lordes ſpiritual (as you cal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11227:12"/> them) and making one miniſter hygher then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother<note place="margin">Repealing of ſtatutes</note> / appoynting alſo an order to ordayne miniſters / which order is cleane differing from the * ſcriptures / wherefore you muſte haue the<note place="margin">Act. 1. 31. Act. 6. 3 Act. 14. 23 1. ti. 3. 2. 7 Tit. 1. 6.</note> order for theſe things drawne oute of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures / which order is this. When any pariſhe is deſtitute of a paſtor / or of a teacher / the ſame pariſh may haue recourſe to the next confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / and to them make it knowne that they maye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> procure cheefely from the one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſities / or if otherwiſe / a man learned / &amp; of good report / <note place="margin">The chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> whome after triall of hys gyftes had in theyr conference / they may preſent vnto the paryſhe which before had bene wyth them aboute that matter / but yet ſo / that the ſame pariſhe haue him a certaine time amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them / that they may be acquainted wyth his gifts and behauioure / and geue their conſentes for his ſtay amongſte them / if they can alleage no iuſt cauſe to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> for he may not be ſent away again / which is ſo ſent to a pariſhe / except a iuſt cauſe of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking / the cauſe alleaged being iuſtly proued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hym / either amongſt themſelues in theyr owne conſiſtorie / ſo that he will appeale no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for hys triall / or els in the next conference / or counſell prouinciall / or nationall / vnto which from one to another he may appeale / if he fynde hymſelfe cleare / and if he geue ouer / they maye proceede as afore for another. And when ſuche an one is founde / to whome the pariſhe muſte <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> geue conſent / bicauſe there is no iuſt cauſe to be alleaged agaynſte him / the nexte conference by whoſe meanes he was procured / ſhall be certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of the pariſhes liking / wherupon they ſhall amongſt themſelues / agree vpon one of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters / which ſhall be ſent by them to the ſame pariſhe / and after a ſermon made according to the occaſion / and earneſt prayer to God wyth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11227:12"/> faſting according to the example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures made by that congregation to God / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it would pleaſe him to direct them in theyr choiſe / and to bleſſe that man whome they chooſe / he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to know their conſent / which being grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / he &amp; the elders ſhall lay their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds on him / <note place="margin">1. ti. 4. 14.</note> to ſignifie to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is lawfully called to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe to be paſtor there / or teacher. Now / for as much as I haue made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of a paſtor / and a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> teacher / of a conſiſtory in each pariſh / of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence / and of a counſell prouincial / and national / I wil as brefely as I can declare / what eache of theſe meaneth / and what the vſe of them is. Ther is required in euery wel reformed church theſe two things: A righte miniſterie *<note n="g" place="margin">mat. 9. 38</note> of the worde and ſacraments / and a right <note n="h" place="margin">mat. 18. 17</note> * gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the churche / which two things are by our ſauioure commended to hys church / before there were any churches gathered. And in the Apoſtles time / when they had gathered ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall churches or congregations / they not onely teache what ſhoulde be / but they eſtabliſhe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders accordingly. In the miniſterie therefore / after rehearſall made of thoſe rare and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie functions of Apoſtles / Prophets / and Euangeliſtes / there is declared in the laſt place thoſe ordinarie functions of *<note n="i" place="margin">Epheſ. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 11. 12. 13. Two ſorts of miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters only. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / and wherein they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke.</note> ſhepheards and teachers / which endure in euery well ordered <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> church / till we all meete together into the vnity of faythe and knowledge of the ſonne of God. There are then in the miniſtery only two ſortes of miniſters / namely paſtors &amp; teachers / which doe not differ in dignitie / but in diſtynction of office / and exerciſe of theyr gifts / and yet in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things their office is ſo like / that they are confounded in the name of Elders / as alſo the gouernours are with the miniſters in the ſame name confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. But theſe two offices differ in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:11227:13"/> this / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the paſtor or paſtors / are they y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> haue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ouerſight &amp; charge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole pariſh / to inſtruct to admoniſh / to exhort / &amp; to correct bi doctrine al and euery one in the aſſemblies or in the priuate houſes of the ſame pariſhe / and to miniſter the ſacraments in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame pariſh. The teacher (ſaue that in the conſiſtory of the ſame pariſhe / and in all conferences of miniſters / he is to beioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the miniſters) ſhall in ſuch places as prouiſion is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> made for him / &amp; being lawfully called as afore / onely intend lectors / and expoſitions of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures / to the end that there may be ſet furth / and kepte a ſoundnes of doctrine / a right &amp; naturall ſence of the ſcriptures / and playne and manifeſt proues of the articles of the Chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſo that he oughte to be an exquiſite and mighty man in the ſcriptures. The vſe of ſuche an one<note place="margin">The vſe of the doctors office.</note> is moſt nedeful / wher the frie of the churche (as I might call it) is / to enter them well which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> ſhuld be emploied to the miniſtrie / whether it be in the vniuerſitie or elswhere / that ſuch be brought vp to this turne. So that in deede the titles of oure vniuerſitie doctors / and bachelors of diuinitie / are not onely for vayn glory ſought<note place="margin">Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doctors and bachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie.</note> and graunted / but there they are the names of courſe / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferred rather by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> prophane iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of them that know not what office of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church they belong too / and by the importunate ſute and meanes made / by ſuch vaine men as deſire to clime / and to haue hygh names / and alſo of a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> blinde cuſtome partly / which (beſydes the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces gotten eaſely by frendſhip / or corrupt brthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie / compounding I ſhould ſay / althoughe no ſhew of learning be vttered / nor exerciſes kept) doth in reſpect of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner throw theſe titles vpon many dolts / which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do / nor can do any thing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is required in a teacher or doctor. And a plaine caſe it is / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11227:13"/> and outwarde glorye is ſoughte by theſe names / &amp; by the name of maſter of Arte / which is eſteemed many degrees beneathe the titles of Doctor / or Bachelor in diuinitie / for otherwiſe they would not offer thoſe titles to ſuche as the vniuerſities would ſhewe pleaſure vnto / as to noble men and others / as though they were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble names / nobilitating them that otherwiſe wer vnnoble / and adding to their nobilitie that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> them were noble. And thus haue they tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpſide downe / and made a mockery of God hys or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> / conferred vpon his churche for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the ſame / excepte they will not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to profeſſe themſelues heerein to folowe the<note place="margin">Heatheniſh tradition.</note> heatheniſh tradition of prophane ſcholes which rather ſeke by ſuche titles to aduance learning / as they ſay / then by their learning to aduan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage the church of God. For none other are true tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers or doctors / but they which doe teache / and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> be founde meete / and be called by the churche to teache / how ſo euer the vniuerſitie doctors ſeeme to haue ſome indelible Caracter / that once and euer doctor / as the popiſhe prieſtes once ſhauen / were euer prieſtes / and can neuer be no prieſtes after / but ſuch doctors as theſe / though they had neuer ſo many graces / ſhall be but idol doctors / as truely doctors / as an image <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a man / whych hath nothing but the ſhew of a man / eyes and ſee not / eares and heare not / and ſo they / teachers &amp; doctors / and teache not. Theſe vaine names be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> ſuche vaine men / but the churche of God they become not / and are forbidden by oure ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure. * <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 23. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Be not you called Rabbines / and to be called Rabbines is the matter with oure doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors / but to teach / that is to baſe or needeleſſe for them. I haue ſpoken the mere of thys / bicauſe the abuſe is great / and not thoughte of / for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it will be faced out / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name is not a name
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11227:14"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f dignitie / but a name of duety to be done to the church of God / by him that hath y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> excellent gyft of faithfull &amp; right expounding of the ſcriptures / and of the vndoubted prouing and auouching of all the articles of our chriſtian religion / whych is moſte requiſite in place where I ſaid before / and very requiſite euery where / &amp; is to be had where competent prouiſion may be made for ſuche an one. Thus you ſee breefely howe theſe two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer / and what is the vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teachers or doctors <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> office. Now the paſtors in their charges and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes<note place="margin">The vſe of the paſtors office / and that it is re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiſite in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</note> / haue not only to propounde ſounde doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine / but alſo charge to exhort / and to admoniſh publiquely and priuately them that they finde to neede it / and to examine them / and to Cathechiſe them in their faith / vpon whome onely lyeth the charge of the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation / whether there be a teacher / or doctor or no. For if the doctor faithfully kepe his lectures / and anſwer hys cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by godly life there is no further thing to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> required of him / ſaue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in the conſiſtorie (againe I ſay) he app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y hymſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the paſtors to guide and directe the reſt of the aſſiſtantes / and in lyke ſorte ioyne himſelfe with the paſtors in theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences councels / and ſuch like meetings. But euery congregation muſt haue a paſtor / I ſaye not a parſone vicare or ſtipendarie prieſt / or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate (as they call him) but a paſtor or ſhepherd / which is able / and dothe intend feeding of them / euery way / by preaching doctrine / by exhorting <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> to the ſame / and to godly life / by admoniſhyng offenders / by conference wyth them / by viſityng the ſicke / to teache and counſell them / by Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing the congregation / by making prayers / by miniſtring the ſacraments / and examining before hand the communicantes / and whatſoeuer he is directed vnto by the preſcripte of the woorde of God. And theſe two offices thus ſet vp / accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11227:14"/> to the ſcriptures / there remaineth no vſe<note place="margin">The good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> enſueth of the erecting of a ryghte miniſterie.</note> of fat canons / prebendaries / petie canons / ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging men / quireſters / virgirs / and the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crue / nor yet of rouing preachers / which preach quarter ſermons / nor of ſtipendarie curates / &amp; that vnbrideled (vntituled cleargye I ſhoulde ſay) but that the liuings of the former might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtowed vpon the maintenance of the righte miniſterie / and the latter to be no longer an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> burden to the churche. And further / ſuch prouiſion being made / there ſhalbe no nede of ſuch dignities / as they call them / nor of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications for many benefice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / as pluralities / trialities / totquors / and I wot not what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of benefices / or prebends vpon biſhops / to amende their liuings forſothe. All thys good commeth of the erecting of a right miniſterye / beſides the faithfull diſcharging of ſo greate a charge as the feedyng of Chryſtes flocke is. And alſo thys I ſay / it is ſo farre of that anye can take vyon him the charge whych our Lord Biſhops do / as they ſay / one of them to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<note place="margin">L. biſhops take farre more charge vpon them / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge.</note> (paſtor they ſeme to meane) of a whole dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe (moſte dioceſſes containing diuers ſhires) yea / and ſome one of a prouince (containing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dioceſſes) that in de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de it is in manner too much for one to take charge of one only pariſh / and to ſay truth / if euery paryſh were able (as it wold be prouided for / by reſtoring impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> by augmenting of the liuings / &amp; by ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning moe paryſhes in one) if euerye paryſhe I<note place="margin">Reſpects require <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtors ouer one flocke then one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer many.</note> ſay / were by ſome ſuche meanes made able / it were meete euery paryſhe had two paſtors at leaſt / bothe for the common charge that lyeth vpon the ſhoulders of the paſtors / and for ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry vſes that theyr congregations haue to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them vpon / or cheefely / bicauſe in the ſyck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the one / the other myght ſupplye. And
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11227:15"/> the paſtor or paſtors being ryghtly called / maye not be put away / but for ſuch cauſes / and in ſuch ſort as was ſayd before / nor he or they maye not leaue their charge / for he or they haue a neceſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty * <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cor. 9. 16. The paſtor maye not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaue hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lock at hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure.</note> of tarying on theyr charge laide vpon them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their charge / except by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good order o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches it be thought expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / or when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepe are wolues / &amp; ſo they dryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them: ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> our reſignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wil not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> word of god / m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch leſſe wil our non reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts abide y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> triall / both ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couerouſneſſe of gredy bellied wolues / the one to fleece wythout care of feedyng / excepte it be themſelues eyther in ſome chaplams roume / or in ſome other ſtye / to ſpare theyr labor where they ſhould entende: The other ſerueth hym that euer gapeth for a greater pray / or to make mony when other ſhyftes ſayle. And further / I wyll not excuſe all thoſe that eyther reſygne / or ſuffer them ſelues to be depryued to auoyde further trouble / wythout conſyderation of theyr flocke / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> if the ſame conſpire not generally againſt them / ſeeing they oughte to giue theyr lyues for their<note place="margin">Ih. 10. 11.</note> flocke. But thys is not thought to be ſo neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full / nor in deede were ſo nedefull / if to reade the ſcryptures / the homilyes / and the courſe of oure booke of common prayers were mough / for then a boy of ten yeares olde may do the miniſters of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice / for the ſubſtance of their offyce is not in the yeares / but in the reading. And in deede boyes and ſenceleſſe aſſes are oure common minyſters <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> for the moſte parte / for / but common reaſon may ſerue thys turne / and doe thys feat well mough. It is in deede leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> buſye then popyſhe prieſtes<note place="margin">Our courſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> religyon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtroyeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys care of Chryſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocke.</note> ſeruyce / bycauſe the kalender and the rubrikes of the booke are fewer: and playner then his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuiſe and pie were / ſo that leſſe clarkes then po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſhe prieſtes / whych had but ſome blinde La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin in their b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly / may ſerue for our ſtore / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11227:15"/> in deede the blindeſt buſſarde of them / if hee wyll keepe hys conſcience to hymſelfe / nay he is not ſo narowly loked vnto / if he wyll ſubſcribe to our Articles of Chriſtian religyon before hys ordinarye / and blindely reade them at hys bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyces / he ſhall not onely be ſeruing prieſt (I vſe their owne termes) but he may haue one Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce or moe / and nothyng ſhall / nor may be ſayde againſt hym / and ſo he proui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hys quarter ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> or pay his Ordinarie for that default and ſuche lyke / he is as good a Paſtor as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt. And yet I thynke verely / the laſte Parliament<note place="margin">A good ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> laſt parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / taketh little effecte / by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> negligence and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ordinaries as they call them.</note> ſaue thys / meant very well in this reſpecte / by a ſtatute prouided in this caſe / ſo that many a leud Prieſt of them (if the Ordinarie had bene good / not being corrupted by bribes / or by their bribed offycers and ſeruaunts) would haue bene remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / and the benefyces readye for better paſtors / but I can heare of none / of few ſo badde / but he <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> is where he was / and my Lorde Byſhoppe hys great frende commonly / for it ſeemeth by ſome of them / that they ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll my Lords the Byſhoppes meanyng / is to make their hande nowe / and to money themſelues nowe / and prouide for their wyfe and children ſomewhat, honeſtly (I will not ſay pompouſly) for fear of after claps againſt a rainye day / whatſoeuer tyme or change come / and thys humoure theſe Prieſtes / and all other Time ſeruers f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> full handſomely / and it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth their purpoſes in deede fullye. No / no / thys is not that myniſterie / whych we haue ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of / and whych God erected in hys churche / reading<note place="margin">Reading of Homilyes came in by abuſe / and maintenieth an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> an Homilie / is Popiſhe and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd / whether they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edes homilies / or anye other auncient wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters homilies / whych in tymes paſt vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyke erroure were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ſed ſo ſupplie the lyke lacke of preaching a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoughe afterward they red them or ſung them in an vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> tongue: or they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:11227:16"/> our biſhoppes homilies in oure owne tongue / for fayth commeth by hearing / and hearing not by homilies: but by the * <note n="o" place="margin">Ro. 10. 17 The mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of faith is the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the ſame.</note> worde of God / &amp; in deede readyng of the word is as good / and better prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching / then readyng of homilies / but the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of faythe is the preaching of the ſame / oute of the woorde of God / by them that are ſent of God. How ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they preach except they be * <note n="p" place="margin">Ro. 10. 15</note> ſent / as it is wrytten / howe beautifull are the feete of them whych bryng good tidings of peace: they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> muſt be ſent of God / endued wyth the gyftes of God / furnyſhed wyth hys graces vnto that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie / that they may be able to bring the good tidings of peace / and good thyngs to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations / that their feete may be beautifull to them / that they may knowe that they are iewels of God beſtowed vpon hys churche / that euerye churche may be aſſured they haue a treaſure of their miniſter or miniſters. Thys is the ryghte <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> way to bryng y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> miniſterie into credyte and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation<note place="margin">The waye to bring the miniſterie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto credite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> / their giftes giuen them of God / &amp; theyr paynfulneſſe / and honeſt lyfe amongſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations / &amp; not to make ſome of them Lordes / Graces / Earles / Prelate / and Regiſter of the Garter / Barons / Suffraganes / ſome of them ryche Deanes / Archdeacons / maſters of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges / Chauncellors / Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ndes / rych perſons and vicares / and thoughe ſome of them be poore inoughe / to gette them credite by their rochets / hoodes / cappes / clokes / tippets and gownes / or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> ſuche lyke implements vſed by the * <note n="q" place="margin">Math. 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. 7. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur ſauior orbiddeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers to ſeke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be noted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> outward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>parel and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſes.</note> Phariſeis whyche claimed hyghe roumes / and made large borders on their garmentes / &amp; loued to be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / and to be called Rabbi / whyche thyngs by our ſauioure are forbidden his miniſters / and an order enioyned / that they which loke for it / ſhuld not haue it / but be leaſt eſteemed. Thys is true / reade the ſcriptures youre ſelues I pray you / if
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11227:16"/> you finde it not ſo / diſproue vs / if it be founde ſo / ſtrengthen vs by your authorities / and lette the worde of God haue the free courſe that it ought to haue. They be but pretences to ſerue the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious courſe that ſome of oure miniſters are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into / when they ſay / it is the credyte of the miniſterie / and the vpholding of the ſame / and thys way of oures / is the diſcrediting and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of the miniſterie / &amp; of all good orders / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> and to bring confuſion into the churche / and as they pretende playne Anabaptiſtrie. But they are no better but pretences and flat vntruthes / for it is God hys owne order ſet by our ſauioure and hys Apoſtles in his church / and I truſt (as breefely as I can) to make it appeare to be God his order / and the leſt order / and the onely order which ſhould be in the churche of God. And as<note place="margin">The coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous abuſes that are too common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the byſhops.</note> for the order whych they pretend to be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them / it may be that they knowe their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when they ride in their ſcarlet roa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es before <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> the Queene / and howe to poll their cleargye as they call them / and all other in their dioceſſes / &amp; howe to leaſe oute benefices to the patrones / or by the perſone or vicare and patrones meanes royally to leaſe them out to ſome other / or to ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enate the houſe / or the gleebe for a round ſumme of money to their Lordſhips cheſtes / or brybes to their wiues / or to their children / or to their offycers / or ſeruauntes / that they may haue their ſhare thereby / or how to kepe their courtes / and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> gette them officers for their beſt aduauntage / or howe to rattle vp theſe new fellowes / theſe yong boyes that will not obey at a becke to their arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles / aduertiſements / canons / caueates / and ſuch lyke ſtuffe of their owne forging / or whatſoeuer proceedeth / or is from / or: for their Lordly eſtate and degree / or howe to pleaſure their frende / or frendes / or freendes freende / with a Benefice / 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11227:17"/> or wyth a Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſo that it maye bee a good turne to themſelues / comming by ſimonie away / or howe to leaſe out their owne temporaltyes of their biſhopprickes / yea &amp; poſſible akenate them from their ſucceſſors / and howe to matche their ſonnes and their daughters together / with great ſummes of money paſſing betweene them / and how to purchaſe lands and leaſes in their wiues &amp; childrens names / bicauſe if they were prieſts / their children cannot inherite / nor are legitimate <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> by the lawes / and howe to raiſe fines and rentes / and many ſuche good orders moe / they are verye ſkilfull in / and keepe very diligently. I woulde for experience / ſome of their doings were exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / and then no doubt we ſhoulde ſee manye of<note place="margin">Examinati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings very expedient.</note> theſe goodly orders brought to lyght. And tyll it be examined / I would that they whych are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men / woulde bryng to lyghte their doings whych they knowe / for as finely as they haue ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled the matters / there are ſome which know <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> inough / and I truſt they will impatt it ere long to the ſtate / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they whych are of ſo ſharp a ſight to ſee who offende them / may themſelues lie ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and ſhew how they offend God and his church / and howe vtterly vnneceſſary they are / and to be remoued from their roumes / and their roumes from the churche / whych by them are continued to ſtall the popiſhe Biſhops in their pompe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine / if euer their tyme ſerue them heere. For good orders / lette vs heare any one they make / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> but euen as the lawe directeth them / which any other temporall officers myght / and woulde doe as well as they / if the lawes dyd not prohibite it. And there is none other but lawes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them / no God his booke / no brotherly talke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them / they will not runne in a premunire for any of all their brethren / nor for any of God hys matters neyther / they will not haue the Queenes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11227:17"/> for any of them all / they wil not be defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced<note place="margin">The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops owne talke / and extreme cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>elties.</note> whatſoeuer commeth of it / nay they wil raile vpon / and reuyle their brethren / they will perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and priſone them / they will ſtirre her maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and all other agaynſt them / they will ſterue / ſtiffle / and pine them to death. Howe many good mennes deathes haue they bene the cauſe of / by an inwarde ſorrowe conceyued of their doings? howe ſodainly dyed maſter Pullen after they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to rage? M. Horton? M. Caruell and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> others? and howe did they kill y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> good mannes heart / olde good M. Couerdale? although they pretended they wold prouide for him / after much adoe from the counſell / and as they ſay / from the Queene to them / &amp; yet they allotted hym a ſmall portion / and paide hym by fittes / and ſometymes wyth baſe golde / and mony if they had any worſe then other / whych I haue heard very crediblye reported. Olde D. Turner was muche behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> to them / being a good man / &amp; an auncient preacher / neuer ſhauen nor greaſed / &amp; yet he had no ſmall ſtirre by them / M. Leauer / M. Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon / and ſome other / at this day learned &amp; godly / howe haue they greeued their good heartes? vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly leauing ſome of them wythout lyuing / to the wyde worlde / to ſhifte as they can. And yet they may not ſhyfte ſome of them by thoſe giftes whych God hath giuen them / they may neyther preache / nor teache chyldren publikely nor pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> And they that are in ſome liuings / what ſorowe doe they holde them wythall / and howe tickliſhly doe they holde them to / euermore in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being called before the hyghe Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners / and to looſe thoſe liuings. How many haue they driuen to leaue the miniſterie / and to liue by Phiſicke / and other ſuche meanes / or to leaue their countrey? Howe many ſtudents haue they diſcouraged from the ſtudie of diuinitie / and to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11227:18"/> chaunge their mindes ſince they ſawe their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings / and to chaunge their ſtudies alſo? Howe many poore Artificers and other commoners in this citie / and elſewhere / haue they ill entreated? brought vp ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders vpon? and by their ill vſage and lacke of diligent conference / haue they not ſuffered to fall / but haue bene the cauſe that they haue fallen into errors? Contrarywiſe / what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and fauor haue they ſhewed to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts? how haue they opened their eares to their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> complaints againſt the miniſters / and ſhut their eares when Papiſts haue bene complained vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / or ſlightly ouerpaſſed it. Yea ſome of them haue ſayde / that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable Papiſtes were more<note place="margin">I wis you ſhall ſynde Preciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / as you call them / bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubiects then theſe / as b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d as you make them.</note> tollerable then theſe preciſians and godlye men that ſeeke for reformation? Hanſon of Oxforde / whych amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt other articles was charged iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / and is yet to be proued that he ſayde Storie was an honeſt man / &amp; was put to death wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully / and had frendes alyue would reuenge hys <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> death one day / howe ſlightly dyd the Byſhop of Canterbury vſe hym: what frendſhippe founde Thurlbie in hys houſe? may poore preachers be halfe ſo wel vſed / or ſuch other poore men / which led by the word of God / doe freely vtter their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences againſt the abuſes in our Reformation? Or rather ſhal not they find harder dealyng then Hanſon did: will not they take on more agaynſte the author of thys booke and ſuche lyke / then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hanſon? Lette vs proceede / who be their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> Chauncelloures? but moſt ſuſpected papiſtes / I heare not of one of them that is no briber. Who be their ſummers but the verteſt varlets? What are the Canoniſtes? What are they but ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Papiſtes? and where haue they their moſte countenaunce / but of the byſhops? to be theyr cheefeſt doers / and hyghe Commiſſioners wyth them / to wryng their brethren / if they be God
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11227:18"/> hys children / and to let papiſtes ſcape ſcotterfree / or to be punyſhed but lyghtly: what cauſes deale they in for the good of the church? certainly fewe at all / but as they ſhould doe they deale in none. How are matters dealt in in their courts / but all for miſtreſſe money? who can recken their diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? in thoſe former Treatiſes you reade of a bleſſed companie / doe you not? howe ſtiffe &amp; ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die are they in the maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their diſorders? how haue they ſhaken of the honeſt ſutes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> honeſt worſhypfull citizens and others: yea / of honorable perſonages whych haue dealt with them for thoſe whome themſelues ought to haue had moſt care of? Howe lyghtly haue they eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the learned letters of manye famous men at home / &amp; abrode / wrytten vnto them in the ſame caſe? howe many honeſt men haue they by their flatterie and tirannie peruerted / and drawne to their ſide? wherof many lyue wyth wounded co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences at thys day amongſte them / and yet for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> feare of loſſe of lyuyng (for they muſte haue a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing they ſay) doe therfore ſerue the biſhops ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites. What a charge are they to their clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie? and what a ſumme haue they yeerely / that myght be ſaued? and it is no ſmal matter y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth their courtes / all whych charges myght be ſaued alſo / and matters belonging to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the church myght be better / &amp; more godly ended. To conclude thys parte wythall / what is more expreſly forbidden in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcriptures / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> then thoſe names and offices whych they haue. Oure ſauioure ſayth expreſly to hys Apoſtles / <note n="*" place="margin">Luke. 22. 25. 26.</note> you ſhal not be called gracious Lords: and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were as <note n="*" place="margin">Apoſtles as worthy to haue ben Lordes / as our biſhops but they might not / being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden it.</note> worthy as any miniſters were ſince / or ſhall be / yea / they were the Archbuyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders / not the Archbiſhops / nor was there anye Archbuilder of them one more then another / and not anye ſince are allowed to haue the name of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11227:19"/> Archbuilders. And albeit any woulde haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them gracious Lords / and geuen it them / yet they myghte not haue taken it / but oure menne though they haue vſed the ſame texte / and other learned men as a playne text vſe it alſo / agaynſte<note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</note> the dignitie that the Pope chalengeth aboue all other byſhops / and againſt hys two ſwordes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet it meaneth no ſuche matter wyth oure men / but that they may be Lords ouer their brethren / and vſe ciuill iuriſdiction alſo. It forbiddeth them to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> ſeeke it / they ſay / but if it be offered to them / they take it. Our ſauioure refuſeth to deuide the land<note place="margin">Luke. 12. 13. 14. Ioh. 6. 15. Ih. 18. 36. mat. 20. 28</note> betweene the two brethren when it was offered hym / he auoydeth when they ſoughte to make hym a king? what thinke you he would haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it / if it had bene orderly offered by the whole ſtate? no / he ſayth: my kingdome is not of thys worlde / or a worldly kingdome / I came not to be miniſtred vnto / but to miniſter / and euen ſo he telleth hys diſciples / it muſte be amongſte them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> And yet further / dothe that text forbid ambition in the miniſters / and allowe it in princes? for he diſproueth not the kings that they are lordes / and exerciſe authoritie ouer their nations / and haue great titles / for not onely there / but the ſcripture is playn / that they may ſo doe / and yet not be am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious / whych they may be / if they contente not themſelues wyth their owne countreys / and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles / but couet others. But in thys place he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> / that they muſte not exerciſe authoritie as<note place="margin">mat. 20. 27 If biſhops <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe take Lordſhyp vpon them others are forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1. Pet. 5. 3</note> ciuill magiſtrates doe / and may doe / nor be one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue another / you ſhall not be ſo / he that is cheefe among you / let hym be your ſeruaunte / ſo that if they will take it / it may not be giuen them. The apoſtles / they alſo auoided it amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues / and they forbid it in others / as the place of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is playne / and ſo playne / that it is a worldly wyſe way to ſeeke ſome other ſhyfte to face oute
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11227:19"/> the matter / and to vnderprop thys ruinous Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie wythall. The ſcryptures are playne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt it / and therfore ſome other deuice muſt be found at a pynche / to flap the world in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mouth wyth ſomewhat: to tel them that good and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient chronicles make mention of the lordly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of biſhops / and to bring forthe the heraldes craft to helpe out the matter / to blaſe the armes of ſuch worthy prelates as haue ben of long time before. This were a worldly wiſe way / and as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> I heare / is entended to be practiſed. But ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if thys be practiſed / they muſt alſo practiſe to ſtoppe the courſe of the ſcriptures / for elſe the ſcriptures will on the other ſide diſplay as faſte / the follie of ſuche proude men. Heere ſome keepe hote ſchooles / what ſay they / euery one as good as another amongſt the miniſters? ſhall not one be better then another? what is diſorder if thys be not? well thys is God hys order / and in dede as I ſayd afore / the beſt order. How is that ſaith <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> another? Thus I ſay. Firſt / let no one mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter meddle in any cure ſaue hys owne / but as he<note place="margin">Not one miniſter to meddle in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nothers cure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out order.</note> is appointed by common conſent of the next con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference / or counſels (as afore) prouinciall or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall / or further if it may fall out ſo / generall of all churches reformed: A conference I call the meeting of ſome certaine miniſters / and other brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as it might be the miniſters of London / at ſome certaine place as it was at Corinth / or<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14 A confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> of ſome certaine deanrie / or deanries in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> / as it might be at Ware / to conferre and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe them ſelues in propheſying / or in interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſcriptures / after the which interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / they muſt conferre vppon that whiche was done / and iudge of it / the whole to iudge of thoſe that ſpake / and yet ſo / as ſome one be appoynted by all / to ſpeake for them / as they ſhall amongs them ſelues agree what ſhall be ſpoken / whych
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11227:20"/> thyng was alwayes vſed among the Apoſtles / one to ſpeake for the reſt / whych co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferences may ſometime be more generall then other ſometime / as occaſion of the Churches may require / to call the brethren together. At which conferences / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one / or any certaine of the brethren / are at the order of the whole / to be employed vppon ſome affaires of the church / which they ſhall ſhewe to be needefull for the ſame. So was Iohn &amp; Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> ſent by the Apoſtles to Samaria / to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme<note place="margin">Act. 8. 14.</note> Philips worke. So was Paule and Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas ſent from Antioche to the buſineſſe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them by the Lord / and yet ſo (which I wold<note place="margin">Act. 13. 2.</note> haue well marked) that the holy Ghoſt ſayde to the congregation: Separate me Barnabas and Saule for the worke whereunto I haue called them / he myght haue called them forth wythout theſe words to them of the aſſemblie / but that he would ſhewe how he approued of that order / and the more the order is commended / that he would <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> haue Saule / one of his Apoſtles / to be thus ſent by thoſe wherof none were of the Apoſtles. At thys aſſembly alſo / the demeanours of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may be examined / and rebuked / as Paule witneſſeth he did in an aſſembly rebuke Peter.<note place="margin">Gala. 2, 14</note> Thys is that which I call a conference / where ſondry cauſes within that circuit / being brought before them / may be decided and ended. But it is to be vſed continually / for the exerciſe of the miniſters / and others / as it ſhoulde ſeeme by the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> Apoſtle in the place to the Corinthes / to exerciſe their gates in the interpretation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. I call that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ynode pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nciall / whych is the meeting of certaine of the conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtorie of euery pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Synode prouincial / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ationall &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nerſall.</note> wythin a prouince / which is of manye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences / as it myghte be that whyche is called Canterburies prouince / if it be not to large / and therefore of ſome one or moe dioceſſes: where
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11227:20"/> great cauſes of the churches / whych could not be ended in their owne conſiſtories / or conferences / ſhall be heard and determined / and ſo they ſhall ſtande / except when a more generall Synode / and councell of the whole land be / whych I call nationall / and they will haue it hearde there / to whoſe determination they ſhall ſtande / excepte there be a more general Synode of all churches / and that they will haue it heard there / and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> whereto they ſhall ſtande / as it was at Ieruſalem / except it be a great matter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth / or a great matter expreſly agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures / as that was in the Nicene councell of the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of miniſters / where the whole councel wold haue concluded agaynſt it / had not one manne Paphnutius wythſtoode them / or that aſſembly<note place="margin">Ioh. 7. 51</note> where Nicodemus onely withſtoode the reſt / or that at Antioche where Peter and Barnabas<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 14</note> and all the Iewes were entred into a diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> / and onely Paule wythſtoode them. In which caſe the ſcripture ſaythe / you haue one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / one maſter / and heare him / and examine all things / and holde that whych is good / and trye the ſpirites whether they be of God / or no / and<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 8. 9. Mat. 17. 1. Th. 52 1. Ih. 4. 1 Galat. 1.</note> againe ſayeth the apoſtle: Though we or an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from heauen preache any other goſpell vnto you then that whych we haue preached vnto you let hym be accurſed. Except I ſay it be in ſuche <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> a caſe / they muſt ſtande to the determinations as afore. And otherwyſe then thus / let no one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vſe / or chalenge any authoritie out of hys owne charge. And there let hym / or them (if they be two paſtoures or moe in one charge) not only alone meddle wyth the charge of preachyng / and other ſuche partes of the paſtor / but alſo let hym or them in that conſiſtorie / and in all other confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and councels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let the miniſters go before / as I might ſay / and guide the other of the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11227:21"/> and elders / in the gouernment / as it is in the councell at Ieruſalem. But before I ſpeake<note place="margin">Act. 15. 12</note> more of the gouernement / let vs a little conſider of thys order of the election of the miniſters / and theſe exerciſes and conferences for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of ſounde religion / and of the equalitie of miniſters / whether the biſhops courſe be better / or thys be the beſt. Firſt / this is well warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note place="margin">A compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie / and the biſhops order.</note> by the ſcriptures / and theirs is not. Theirs hath already bene the cauſe of many miſcheefes / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> and thys the cauſe of muche good in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue churche / and is ſo ſtill where it is practiſed in the reformed churches beyond the ſeas. This alloweth only painful and true preachers / theirs ignorant Aſſes / loytering and idell bellyed Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures / or prophane and heatheniſhe Oratoures / that thincke all the grace of preaching lyeth in affected eloquence / in fonde fables to make their<note place="margin">Prophane preachers.</note> hearers laughe / or in oſtentation of learning of their Latine / their Greke / their Hebrue tongue / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> and of their great reading of antiquities: when God knoweth / moſte of them haue little further matter then is in the infinite volumes of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note place="margin">Common places and A potheg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> places / and Apothegmes / culled to their hands. But if they carye away the praiſe of the people for their learning / thoughe the people haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned little or nothing at their handes (for they can not learne muche / where little is ſpoken to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) or for ſome mery tales they haue tolde / or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/>
               <note place="margin">Merye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ales.</note> ſuch like pagea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to pleaſe itching eares wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all / ſuche a fellowe muſte haue the benefices / the prebendes / the Archdeaconries / and ſuche lyke loyterers preferments / eſpecially if he can make lowe curteſie to my Lordes / and know his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to euery degree of them / or can creepe into ſome noble mannes fauoure to beare the name of hys chapleine / this is he y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhall beare the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments awaye from all other / and to flaunte it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11227:21"/> out in hys long large gowne / and hys tippet / and<note place="margin">Flaunting preachers.</note> hys little fine ſquare cappe / with hys Tawnie coates after hym / fiſking ouer the citie to ſhewe him ſelfe / none can haue that he may haue / except ſome certaine fatte fellowes / with long bagges<note place="margin">Long bags</note> at their girdels / and ſome in their ſleeues / or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a dyſhe of M. Latuners apples. Corruption / too muche corruption in theſe matters. Thys order auoydeth intruſion into any benefices / but to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> choſen by the conſent of that pariſhe where they ſhall be minyſters / and there to tary. Theirs / ſo the patrone preſent / and the biſhoppe inſtitute / thruſteth vppon pariſhes ſuche / as what ſo euer they are / they cannot be refuſed / and may reſigne or otherwyſe departe as they liſte. Theirs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynteth not onely moe hoy miniſters / &amp; dumbe dogges not able to barke / then they wot where to beſtowe / but alſo many rouing preachers / to preache in whoſe cure they liſt / out of all order. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> Thys / appoynteth euery paſtor to hys charge / and by a very good order / none to meddle out of hys owne charge. By thys / all wythout excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / are drawne &amp; driuen to exerciſe them ſelues among them ſelues / for the encreaſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge / and for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation of them in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth. Theirs appoynteth at their lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes pleaſure / and their Archdeacons / their men eyther to ſay a parte of one of the Epyſtles wythout booke / or to turne it out of Latine into <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> Englyſhe / or to wryte their fantaſyes of ſome Theme geuen them / wherein there is muche good ſtuffe if it were well knowne / or to learne M. Nowels Catechiſme by roate / rather then by reaſon / or if they haue ſome exerciſes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying any where / it is ſo rawe / and wythoute order / except perhaps an order not to ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of their proceedings / that as good ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a whit / as neuer the better. Thys ſheweth a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11227:22"/> ready and a right way / to reſolue all doubts and queſtions in religion / and to pacifie all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies of the churches / to paſſe from one or few to moe / &amp; from moe / to moe godly and learned / to be decided by them / according to the truthe and worde of God. Theirs raiſeth many douts and queſtions in religion / breedeth many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and contentions / and wyl haue nothyng ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined that they doe / but many muſt ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> pleaſure of ſome one of them / and all muſt abide the determination of one / ſuche Lordſhyp they claime ouer the faithe of their chriſtian brethren.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 1. 24.</note> The Apoſtle renouncing it / and acknowledging hymſelfe to be a helper. If they ſay Lordſhyppe of biſhops is agreeable to the word of God / who may ſay agaynſt them / wythout much trouble? yea / dare ſay againſt them? yea / what preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it to ſay againſt them / if they hold together? to whom it is to ſwete to ſay ſay agaynſt it / or if my Lords grace / Metropolitane of al England <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> holde / &amp; ſticke faſt in the matter? for ſo it goeth / many muſt to one / &amp; ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one to one / til it come to the Pope of Lambeth / as it was wont in the Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhe church / cleane contrary to the courſe of the ſcriptures / for there is no more ones / but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one one / to whome all the churche muſt obey / and from him / the whole church hath authoritie ouer the membres of the ſame / for ſo goeth the ſcriptures / you haue but one maiſter / all you are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 23. 8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17. 5 18. 17 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e him / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</note> brethren / heare him / and tell the church / thys is the ſcripture. Now / except they will followe the Popes rule / and bryng the vniuerſal churche to be but a particulare place / and a particulare man in that place / as Rome is the place / and the pope is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> man / or as Caunterbury or Lambeth might be the place / and my Lorde hys grace the man / the ſcriptures and their doings will not agree. And hys Lordſhip ſhallbe a Pope / and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11227:22"/> the Popes vnderlings / excepte they leaue their Lordlyneſſe / and ſubmit them ſelues to the church of God / to be ordered by the ſame / according to the woorde. And take them for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / who ſhall / they are none other / but a rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of Antichriſtes broode / and God amende them / and forgeue them / for elſe they bid battell to Chriſt and his church / and it muſt bid the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to them / all they yeelde. And I proteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> the eternall God I take them ſo / and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after wil I vſe my ſelf in my vocation / and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moe to no doubt which be careful of God his glory / and the churches libertie / wyll vſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues agaynſt them / as the profeſſed ennemies of the churche of Chriſt / if they proceede in thys courſe / and thus perſecute as they doe. What talke they of their being beyond y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſeas in Quene Maries dayes becauſe of the perſecution / when they in Queene Elizabethes dayes / are come <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> home to rayſe a perſecution. They boſt they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe<note place="margin">Perſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> raiſed.</note> the ſteps of good maiſter Ridley the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir: let them followe hym in the good / and not in the badde. What man / Martyr or other / is to be followed in all things? why follow they not M. Hooper as well as him / who is a martir alſo? or Rogers / or Bradforde / who are martirs alſo? They ſay all thoſe good men in Quene Marres<note place="margin">The m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyrs in Mary o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dayes / they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red?</note> dayes died for the booke of common prayer / but they ſlaunder them / for they toke not ſo ſlender a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> quarel / they dyed for god his boke / and for a true faith grounded vpon the ſame. Diuers of thoſe martires / would not in thoſe dayes of king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / abide all the orders in that booke / but if they had had ſuch a time beyonde the ſeas in the reformed churches / to haue profited and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in knowledge of a right reformation as theſe men had / it is not to be doubted / but that they would haue done better then he promiſed / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> had
<pb facs="tcp:11227:23"/> rather all England were on a fishpoole / then he would be brought to matters f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r leſſe / then now of hys owne accorde he wilfully thruſteth hym ſelfe vpon. Why we they not followe the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which they ſawe beyonde y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſeas? In which of the reformed churches ſaw they a Lord biſhop allowed? or the Canon lawe to direct church or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? or will they tranſlate the boke of common prayer into Latine / and their pontilicall / and vſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> the Latine of the popiſhe portuiſe / manual / and<note place="margin">Turning y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ficall / unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortuis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue / to try y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>equired.</note> pontifical in thoſe matters wherin they haue fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thoſe bokes / and but tranſlated them out of Latin / and will they require &amp; abide y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the reformed churches concerning the matters? If they be not ſingulare / if they meane plainely / lette them doe thus. If it will abyde the triall / then let them vſe it ſtill. They ſhal not be diſgraced / but we for diſquieting of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They haue f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cendes that will ſaye for them / they are a learned company and ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe not the helpe of any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> other churches. Then let them offer to defende their courſe by learning. Let them neuer goe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſea for the matter (and yet ſurely I woulde ſome toke that tranſlation in hande / &amp; toke ſome paynes in the matter / to procure the iudgements of thoſe reformed churches) but lette them offer free confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce heere at home. Nay / let them take our offer for conference (by wryting to auoyde muche brabble if they will) and ſhew themſelues ready to the ſtate / wythoute cunning practiſe to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> ſtoppe it by their freendes / and let vs ioyne in it freely / and then we will thincke better of them / and yeelde oure ſelues to haue beene deceiued in them / if they deale plainly. O Lord that we wer deceiued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n them. That they were not wickedly bent / to maintaine that which they are entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to / to the great diſquieting of thys Churche of Chriſte in Englande / vntill the Maiſter come / 
<pb facs="tcp:11227:23"/> (which they thinke will deferre hys commyng) and diſquiet them / whome he fynedeth like lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Epicures / eating &amp; drynking wyth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> worldly drunkardes / and beatyng their fellow ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. They that are poore men / already beggered by them / and which haue many wayes b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and impryſoned / ſome in the Marſhalſey / ſome in the white Lion / ſome in the Catchouſe<note place="margin">There is no perſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they ſay / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reporte m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amples.</note> at Weſtmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter / others in the counter / or in the Clynke / or in the Ficete / or in Bridewell / or in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Newgate / they whych haue theſe many wayes and times bene hampered &amp; ill handled by them / they ſtil offer themſelues to al their exercinities / and therefore put for the their treatiſes / becauſe they paſſe not howe deare they bought it / ſo they myght redeme our ſtate out of this defor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation / to a ryght platforme drawne oute of the ſcriptures. They ſay / ſuch are men pleaſers. Surely / if they ſough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e aduauntage that way / it were beſt for them to pleaſe my Lords. They ſay they are deſirous to be ſayd to be in pryſon / &amp;<note place="margin">Vaine an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wicked o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iections.</note> that they profite by it / they would not then kepe themſelues out of the way / nor whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are in / be ſuche ſuters to come toor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he / nor abide to be ſtifeled and choked with the ſtench of the priſon / but that is an old ſhift and cunning of he aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſay ſo. No, no / God hys cauſe is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. You pretend a reformation / and followe not the worde of God / nor will be led by that. The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> ſumme of all therfore is thys / that eyther you of the Parliament muſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake order to haue all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed according to the worde of God / whereof already you haue heard a parte / and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll heare breefely the reſt by God his grace / or elſe they to bryng your reformation to the trial of the word of God / and to ouerthrowe by the ſame all that we ſay / and al that the other of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt reformed churches doe vſe. Well they may conferre and
<pb facs="tcp:11227:24"/> yeelde / for neuer ſhall they ouerthrow the truthe which we vtter / and which the reformed chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches doe practiſe / nor ſhall they be able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their owne doings / but by crueltie / &amp; wl, at ſucceſſe that hath euer had / iudge by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcriptures and by the papiſtes experience. For this order of chuſing of miniſters for their conferences and equalitie therefore / you ſhall proue none to be ſo good as thys / which I haue mentioned / nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> / but that thys oughte to be in a reformed churche. Shall I examine their other orders? y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> were infinite / but yet for the booke of common prayer / which of all other muſte not be touched / <note place="margin">Booke of common prayer.</note> becauſe they haue gotten the ſtate ſo to beare it out / Euen for the very ſtates ſake / for the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſake / for the churches ſake / and for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake / he hath but a badde conſcience that in thys time will holde hys peace / and not ſpeake it for feare of trouble / knowing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there are ſuche intollerable abuſes in it / as it is plaine there are. Firſt I ſay / that if it were praying / &amp; that there were neuer an ill woorde / nor ſentence in all the prayers yet to appoynt it to be vſed / or ſo to vſe it as Papiſtes did their mattens and euenſong / <note place="margin">In intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable abuſe of prayer.</note> for a ſet ſeruice to God / though the woordes be good / the vſe is naught. The wordes of the fyrſt chapter after S. Iohn / be good / but to be putte in a tablet of golde / for a ſoueraigne thyng to be worne / that vſe is ſuperſtitious and naughte / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> and ſo is the vſe of thys ſeruice / for the order muſt be kept / and that being done / they haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued God. And if they alledge that that vſe was not meant / and that it is an abuſe. I ſay and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue it / that if it be an abuſe / it is ſo ſetled it wil not be refor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed / till there be a reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Agayne / wherelearned they to multiplye vp many prayers of one effect / ſo many times Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye be to the Father / ſo manye times the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:11227:24"/> be wyth you / ſo many times let vs pray. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<note place="margin">Gloria pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri. Dominus vobiſcum. Oremus. Kyriele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Many pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſters.</note> learned they all thoſe needeleſſe repetitions? is it not the popiſhe Gloria patri? their Dominus vobiſcum? their Oremus? Lorde haue mercye vpon vs / Chriſte haue mercy vpon vs / is it not kyrie eleeſon / Chriſte eleeſon? their many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſters / why vſe they them? But as though they were at their beades. The words be good / ſo were they when they were in Latine / but the vſe is naught / forbidden by oure ſauioure: you when you pray vſe not vaine repetitions as the<note place="margin">Mat. 6. 7.</note> heathen doe / ſaythe he. And then the Collect for the day to be vſed at ende of mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ens / what ſhall I call it? and afore the epiſtle and goſpel as they call it. The boke is ſuche a peece of worke as it<note place="margin">Reading prayers no praying. In praying many gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vſed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome / then of reaſon &amp; knowledge or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> is ſtraunge we will vſe it / beſydes I cannot accompt it praying as they vſe it commonly / but only reading or ſaying of prayers / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a childe that learneth to reade / if hys leſſon be a prayer / he readeth a prayer / he dothe not pray / euen ſo is it commonly a ſaying / and reading prayers and not praying / the childe putteth of hys cap as wel as the miniſter. For thoughe they haue manye guiſes / nowe to knele / and nowe to ſtande / theſe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of courſe / and not of any pricke of conſcience / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pureing of the heart moſt commonly. One he kneeleth on hys knees / and thys way he loketh / and that way he loketh / another he kneeleth him ſelfe a ſleepe / another kneeleth wyth ſuche deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he is ſo farre in talk / that he forgetteth to ariſe till hys knee ake / or hys talke endeth / or ſeruice is done. And why is all thys? but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there is no ſuche praying as ſhould touche the hearte. And therfore another hath ſo little feeling of the common prayer / that he bryngeth a booke of hys owne / and though he ſitte when they ſitte / ſtand when they ſtande / kneele when they kneele / he may pauſe ſometime alſo / but moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of all he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endetly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:11227:25"/> hys owne booke / is thys praying? God graunt vs to feele oure lackes better then thys / and to take a better order then thys for prayer / it is &amp; will be all naught elſe. Againe / the Pſalmes be all red in forme o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prayer / they be not all pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / the people ſeldome marke them / and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time when they marke them / they thinke ſome of them ſtraunge geare / and all for that they are<note place="margin">Reading <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t pſalmes.</note> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only red / and ſcarſe red oftentimes. It is a very ſimple ſhift that you vſe to ſhift it wyth an Homilie / to expounde darke places of ſcripture / for they be darkly expounded that be expounded / and many places more darke then you rehearſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny whiche are not once touched. Simple and homely geare in diuers homelies there is. There is none other helpe I came tell you / but playne pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ching whych is God hys plaine order.</p>
            <p>What reaſon to ſing the chapters of ſcriptures / <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inging of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ers.</note> and yet ſo they may in a plaine tune. Are all the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> praiers that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed / agreeable to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcriptures? to let paſſe the Benedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tus / where I woulde<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enedic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> knowehowe I might ſay in my prayer: for thou childe ſhalt be called the Prophet of the higheſt / and the Magnificat / where I woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e knowe<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> howe any man / yea / or woman eyther might ſay the tenure of theſe very wordes: for he hathe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded the low degree of hys handmayde / for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde from henceforthe all gencrations ſhall call me bleſſed? marke this well / and you can neuer <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> anſwere it well / but that it is a palpable follye / and vaine praying. To let theſe paſſe / I woulde knowe in what canonicall ſcripture they fynde thys prayer: O all ye workes of the Lorde? and what they meane when they ſay O Anamas / A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarias<note place="margin">Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> / and Miſael prayſe the Lord? which part of prayer is not according to the ſcripture / if all the reſt be / but the whole thankes geuing is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pochriphall / and yet thoſe men that are named / 
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:11227:25"/> were then aliue / &amp; ſayde it themſelues / if it were truely their prayer / and it belongeth not to vs to ſpeake to them nowe / that are deade / and why to them more then to the virgin Marie / Peter or Paule. &amp;c? Let hym that ſpeaketh / ſpeake as the<note place="margin">1. Pe. 4. 11</note> woorde of God / ſayeth the Apoſtle. wyth what truthe can we ſay / that one Collect which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to be ſaide from the Natiuitie to New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeares<note place="margin">Collectes at the feaſt of the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie and Whition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite.</note> day? which is / that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the natiuitie day I muſt ſay / that Chriſte vouchſafed this day to be borne / &amp; when I read it another day / I muſt ſay he vouchſafed thys day to be borne / and the next day againe this day. Surely I lie / one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes / and ſuche a prayer is at whitſontide ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted. I would know wher vpon they grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their Collect appointed for the ſeruice of ſ. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew (for we haue Sametes / and Angels / <note place="margin">A Collecte on Bartho lomewe day.</note> and all Hallowes ſeruice whych the firſt treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſpeake of) I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulde I ſay knowe whereon they ground that Collect? wherein they pray y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they may follow Bartholomews ſermons / ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is neuer a ſermon of hys extant / and ſo we ſhall folow we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t not what? or y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they pray y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the church may preach as he did. when as they neyther haue his ſermones / nor yet the whole church may preach / but the miniſters of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church only. Is thys praying? God forgeue vs / it is a wicked pratling. By what ſcripture haue they Lent ſeruice: A ſowedenſday ſeruice? thre Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects<note place="margin">Seruice for Lent / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſday. &amp;</note> for that day? There is alſo <note n="*" place="margin">A Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</note> a Comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on grounded vppon great reaſon / if that be well marked / which the prieſt (forſothe) muſt ſay at the entraunce into the matter / that is / what a peece of Diſcipline was in former times kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the holy time of Lent / which vntill it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored / would be ſupplied wyth this Iewiſhe <note n="*" place="margin">Deu. 27 13. 14.</note> order. But what place of ſcripture dothe induce them to reduce thys ceremonie? or what place of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11227:26"/> ſcripture woulde warrante ſuche a peece of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline / as there they ſeeme verye deſirous to haue reſtored? as who ſhoulde ſaye ſuche deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of obſcruances for <note n="*" place="margin">Galat. 4. 9. 10. 11.</note> dayes and tymes were profitable or ſutterable in Chriſtes churche. Let them endeuoure to commend god hys diſcipline / whych ſhould be all the dayes and tymes of oure lyfe exerciſed in Chriſtes churche. Let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that. I would knowe what there is in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Creede / that that muſt be vpon hyghe<note place="margin">Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Creede. Venite.</note> dayes (as they terme them) rather then the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Creede: I woulde knowe why Venite may not ſerue at Eaſter as it muſt all the yeare afore / and after folow Domine labia? it is ſurely a ſtraunge thyng to ſee the fanſies that this boke is full of. I ouerpaſſe the dry Communion (as they call it) the Epiſtle / the Goſpel / the Offerto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie / and becauſe they haue in the former treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes touched many things of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts / of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> / of confirmation / &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> reſt / I y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more willingly ſkippe ouer manye things elſe / ſaying ſhortly y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the ſacraments are wickedly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled &amp; prophaned. But as for Confirmation / as it hath no ground out of the ſcriptures at all / ſo I wold<note place="margin">Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> haue their prayer marked / how they recken vp y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſeuenfold grace as the papiſtes did? neither more nor leſſe / where they haue one grace more / then the. 11. of Eſay hath / which they allude to. And again / they haue farre fewer then are mentioned <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> in the reſt of the ſcriptures. Lorde / to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe very follies / may not thys booke be altered ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in matter nor manner? Surely / then haue<note place="margin">A manner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y ſorte of miniſters. Iere. 6. 6. 17. 18. 9. 20. 21.</note> you a mannerly ſort of miniſters that ſtrain cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie to forbeare to lie / and to forbeare ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / when they ſeeme to preſent themſelues before the Lord / which can worſe like ſuch ſeruice then you can to forbeare it. I haue thus much further
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11227:26"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xamined the orders that theſe men vſe in prayer / beſide the generall obſeruation / that they allowe prayer in publique place without a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which is rightlye prohibited in Churches reformed. Would the word of God thus negligently / thus ſantaſtically / prophanely / and heathemſhly be preached? or the ſacraments be ſo wickedly / with out examination at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper / or ſinceritie at bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme / be ſo (I ſay) wickedly miniſtred? woulde prayers be made eyther that were ſo folyſhe / or ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> ſuperſtitious / or ſo falſe / or y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beſt of them ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoutlye / if there were ſuche righte orders as were in the churches planted by the Apoſtles / as is in the beſt reformed churches / and ought to be in oures? What though theſe men be / and wil be taken ſo learned / ſo right / that they neede learne of none other / are not theſe their orders? doe they not maintaine them? doe they not perſecute them that ſpeake agaynſte them? and yet I praye you are they not ſtarke naught? yea / and ſo are diuers <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> of them / not onely for their bribing and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / and their arrogancie / their tyrannie / but for flat hereſie in the ſacrament / and ſome bee ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of the hereſy of Pelagius. For the firſt / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
               <note place="margin">Byſhops the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues / ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hereſies / and ſome ſuſpected. The boke of Articles of chriſtian religion.</note> is concerning the ſacrament / the biſhops are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly knowne which erre in it / and for Free will not onely they are ſuſpected / but others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And in deede the booke of the Articles of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion ſpeaketh very daungerouſly of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> from grace / which is to be reformed / bicauſe it too muche enclineth to their erroure. Other thyngs there are maintained by ſome of them whych are not agreeable wyth the Scrypture: namely the falſe interpretation of thys clauſe in our Creede (he deſcended into hell) whych is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly<note place="margin">The Crede in meter.</note> ſet downe contrary to the ſcriptures in the Creede made in meter in theſe wordes: Hys ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite dyd after thys deſcend into the lower parts / 
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:11227:27"/> to them that lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in darkneſſe were / the true light of their heartes. If they can warrant thys oute of the ſcriptures / then Limbus patrum / &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a while purgatorie will be founde oute there. And yet thys muſt be priuiledged / and ſuche like diuers matters diſagreeing with the ſcriptures / <note place="margin">The hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſute of a ſynner. The laſt great Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> as in the humble ſute of a ſynner it is ſayde / that the Saintes and Angelles ſee Chriſtes bloudye woundes as yet / and in their laſt great Bible in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> the firſt edition of it / ſuch a ſight of blaſphemous pictures of God the father / as what they deſerue for it / I will referre them to none other iudge then their owne note vppon the. 15. verſe of the fourth of Deuteronomie / we holde I wotte not what hereſies that ſpeake agaynſt their pride &amp; traditions / but they that expreſly ſpeake and we againſte the ſcriptures / holde nothyng I trowe but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. But lette theſe guides weyghe the ſcripture / which ſaythe / you ſtrame a gnatte / and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> ſwallowe downe a Camell. Wel now / ſeeing we<note place="margin">mat. 23. 24</note> haue thus farre weyghed / partly God his orders for the miniſters election / for their exerciſes / and for their equalitie / that it is better then oure L. Biſhops / for the continuing of ſounde religion / and that the order of biſhops is contrarye to the ſcriptures / and that they make and maintaine w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crueltie agaynſt the ſcriptures many wicked or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders / let vs nowe come to the other parte / which is of the gouernment of the churche / to ſee howe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> that ſtandeth by the ſcriptures. I haue alreadye made mention of a Conſiſtorie / which were to be<note place="margin">Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wherof it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth. The mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> had in euery congregation. That conſiſteth firſt of the miniſters of the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation / as the guides and mouth of the reſt / to direct them by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcriptures / and to ſpeake at their appoyntment / that whych ſhall be conſented vpon amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them all / bicauſe of their giftes / &amp; place amongſt them / whych maketh them more fit for thoſe purpoſes / 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:11227:27"/> The aſſiſtants are they / whome the pariſh ſhall<note place="margin">Who the aſſiſtantes muſt be.</note> conſent vpon and chuſe / for their good iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and godlineſſe / which they know they be of / wherby they are mete for that office / vſing the aduiſe of their miniſters therin cheefely / and hauing an eye to a preſcript forme drawne out of the ſcriptures / at the appointment of the Prince and ſtate / by the godly learned menne of thys<note place="margin">Howe the aſſiſtantes muſt be choſen.</note> realme / b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rawneſſe of this people yet / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> and alſo vſing earneſt prayers / wyth faſting / as in the choiſe of the miniſter / &amp; hauing made their choiſe thereafter / they ſhall publiſhe their agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their pariſhe / and after a ſermon by their miniſter / at their appoyntment / and vppon their conſent the miniſter may lay hys handes vppon euery of them / to teſtify to them their admiſſion. This conſiſtorie is for that onely congregation / <note place="margin">wherefore thys conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth.</note> and muſt doe that which they we / wyntly in any common cauſe of the churche. And theſe are to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> employe themſelues / and to be employed by that congregation / vpon the neceſſary and vrgent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the ſame churche. Theſe are they in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church / to whome our ſauiour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth them that haue twiſe / or oftner admoniſhed an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / and he heareth them not / to vtter ſuch an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender: when he ſayth / tell the church. Theſe are they / whoſe laſt admonition he of that church / or they which regarde not / ſhall be taken as a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licane<note place="margin">mat. 18. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or heathen. Theſe are they / that ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhe all ſuche in that congregation / as they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> knowe to liue with offence to the church / or as be preſented to them / by good teſtimonie of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed. Theſe be they / which ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate the ſtubburne / making the whole church priuie to their doings / and ſhall vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / take order for the receiuing ſuch an one in againe / making open profeſſion of hys or their repentance / to the ſatiſfying of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> congregation.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11227:28"/> Yet euer ſo muſt they excommunicate / &amp; receiue the excommunicate in againe / that they require the aſſent of their whole congregation / ſhewing<note place="margin">Aſſent of their whole congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> the greuouſneſſe of hys fact / and howe they haue proceeded wyth him by admonition / and hys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt / whych they ſhall doe / bothe bicauſe their vpright dealing may appeare to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whole church / and bicauſe they may not vſurpe authoritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the whole churche / whereby we might caſte <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> out the tirannie of the biſhops / &amp; bryng in a new tyrannie of theirs: who are appointed by good order / to haue the examination of matters / &amp; the reſt of the dealing / in the name of the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. Neuertheleſſe / what they do wel / the congregation cannot alter / neither ſhall the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation put them / or any of them out / but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſt cauſe proued / either in that conſiſtorie / or in ſome one of the counſels / and the cauſe accepted for ſufficient. Neither may they / or any of them <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> leaue to deale in that turne / except they can ſhew good cauſe to that conſiſtorie / and it to be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by them / wyth the conſent of the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation / and good liking. For neyther muſte they lightly be broughte into ſuſpition / nor they muſt not lightly caſt of ſo waighty a calling / and<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 19. Diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onies.</note> function of ſuche importance / no more then the miniſters may. They alſo ſhall examine all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered ceremonies vſed in place of prayer / and aboliſhe thoſe which they finde euill / or vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> / and bring in ſuche orders / as their congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſhall haue neede of / ſo they befew / and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant / neceſſary both for edifying / and profite &amp; decent order: prouing it plainely to the whole<note place="margin">Neceſſary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rders. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eude cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omes.</note> church that it is ſo. And in like ſorte ſhall they ſuffer no lewd cuſtomes to remaine in their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe / either in ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es / or otherwiſe / but hauing conferred of ſuche things amongſte themſelues / they ſhall admoniſh him or them brotherly / that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:11227:28"/> he or they / vſe them not any more / as vnſeming to Chriſtian men to vſe the lyke / or if they be common / they ſhall geue open admonition / and it ſhall be left. In all theſe things / &amp; in all things of the church / they ſhall not meddle wyth the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill magiſtrates office / nor wyth any other pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment<note place="margin">They may not meddle wyth the ciuil magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce.</note> but admonition / and excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the obſtinate. Yet this they muſt doe / that he which hath lyued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offence to that congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> / although he hath ſuffred the puniſhment of the law for hys offence againſt it / yet he ſhall by them be admoniſhed / to ſatiſfie the congregation to whom he hath geuen offence / &amp; amongs who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he dwelleth. As for example: he that hath vſurie<note place="margin">Vſurie.</note> proued agaynſt him / ſo that he loſe hys principal for taking aboue ten in the hundred / yet ſhall he alſo for committing ſo hamous offence agaynſte God / and hys churche / to the very ill example of others / not be allowed to the Sacraments / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> he ſhewe hymſelfe repentaunt for the faulte / and ſtudy thereby to ſatiſfie the congregation ſo offended by him. Theſe ſhal receiue the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<note place="margin">Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coumpts of the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</note> of the deacons / for the releefe of the pore / &amp; their accomptes for that which they ſhal lay out that way / and of their dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in viſiting them / that the congregations maye by the Conſiſtorie be certefyed of all thyngs concerning the poore / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> bothe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there may be made prouiſion according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / and that the prouiſion made / may be wel huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded / and the pore may by the deacons be viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / comforted / and releeued accordyng to their lack. Laſtly / one or moe of theſe aſſiſtants / with one of the miniſters / &amp; a deacon or deacons ſhall<note place="margin">Who ſhu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> repaire to the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faires.</note> be thoſe / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhall at their churches charges meete at the prouincial councell / or nationall / if there be any buſineſſe that concerneth their churche. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially / one of the miniſters ſhall not faile / and one of this aſſiſtance / to be parties in any gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:11227:29"/> cauſe of all the churches that may be dealte in there / whether it be concerning doctryne / or manners. Now a word or two of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / and deacons / becauſe I haue made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of them / and then I will ſhew vpon what ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures theſe orders are groſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed / and a little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them wyth thoſe which we vſe / and ſome certaine matters incident to theſe / &amp; then I will draw to an ende by God hys grace. Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> may not be vſed / but after ſondrye bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly<note place="margin">Of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and ſharpe admonitions too &amp; great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions / offences / and contemptes ſhewed / as the ſcripture is pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. And in theſe caſes they are by the perſons / and order aſore / not ſhut oute of the church dore as we vſe / but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the churche<note place="margin">Shutting out of the churche dore.</note> of God / and communion and felowſhippe of the ſaintes / they are deliuered to ſathan / and to be eſteemed / and to be no more taken for Chriſtian men / till they repent / then Heathens or Turkes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> are / ſaue that / as they may be allowed / yea and procured if it may be to come to heare ſermons / ſo alſo they may be conferred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the brethren / to bryng them to repentance. But they ſhall not be allowed to the ſacrament / the pledge of Chriſt hys league with hys church / vntill by repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they may be admitted as afore is ſayde / into the fellowſhip of the church againe. Neyther ſhall any brother / or ſiſter / vſe hys or their companie / but to admoniſhe them / and exhort them to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> / or as he or ſhe may the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s company / for their neceſſary affaires in the world / as they may haue dealing together / or as a wife / whych<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> may not depart from her huſband if he wil abide with her / and yet ſhee may be admitted to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the congregation / if ſhe contemne not the doing of the churche / but do her vttermoſte to call her huſband home. In like caſe / if it were y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wife that were excommunicated / he ſhuld be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted / 
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:11227:29"/> and not ſhee. Shortly to ſay: Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication<note place="margin">No puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment ſo gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous in this world / as Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> is a fearfull thing / as it is preſcribed by the ſcriptures / and vſed by the Churches of Chriſt reformed accordingly. No puniſhment to it in thys worlde / but onely hell eternally / for he that is in it / eyther he hath hys conſcience ſeered wych a hote iron / I meane it is brawned / and he hath no feelyng / or elſe he cannot be wythout a hell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n hys conſcience: for he is out of the felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp of the Sainctes / he cannot claime to be of Chriſt his body / nor that his promiſes and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy belong to him / if he ſeeke not to be receiued by repentance into the congregation of Chryſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / nor he may not haue that comfortable pledge of Chriſt hys ſupper in fruition with the churche / till hys repentance be accepted by that churche. Neyther may any other church receiue hym / tyll he haue ſatiſfyed that churche / but the<note place="margin">ſome ſhar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t would be prouided b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ciuill magiſtrate for him y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temneth excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication / but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> charge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. What a deacon is. Act. 6. 3.</note> miniſter and conſiſtorie of that church / whereto he newly repaireth / ſhall inquire from whence he came / and haue teſtimonye from thence / and not admit hym / no more then the other churche / or if otherwyſe / to anſwere it at ſome conference or councell prouinciall / or national. And beſides / the ciuil magiſtrate / the nurſe and foſter father o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the churche / ſhall doe well to prouyde ſome ſharpe punyſhment for thoſe that contemne thys cenſure and diſcipline of the church / for no doubt it is in the degree of blaſphemie / of a heathen our ſauioure ſayth / that renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth God / and Chriſt / and thus much of that. A Deacon is an offycer of the church for the behoofe of the poore / choſen to thys offyce by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregation / by ſuch meanes as afore is preſcribed in the choyſe of Elders / by aduiſe and conſent / being a noted man for godly iudgement / and faythfulneſſe / as it is playne out of the ſcryptures / that ſuch a one he ſhoulde be. Hys offyce is to viſite the poore in deede / to loke
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:11227:30"/> diligently what they lacke / and howe many they be / and what be their names / and to certefye the Conſiſtorie / or ſuche a number in one paryſhe they may be / that they ſhall neede a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution / and then the deacon / or deacons / wyth thoſe of the Conſiſtorie afore named / may certe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the counſell prouinciall / that a prouiſion may be leuied for the ſuſtentation of thoſe pore / which prouiſyon ſhall be delyuered into theſe deacons <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> handes / to be deſtributed and turned to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> behoofe of that pore / and to giue an accompt of that they deſtribute / and the reſt in their handes to their owne Conſiſtorie / for that whych is collected there / or they / and thoſe of the conſiſtorie / as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / to certefie it to the councell prouinciall / for the generall contribution / howe it is truely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. Thys offyce howſoeuer papiſtry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e conuerted / or peruerted it / is an offyce needeful / and commaunded to the church of God / vſed by<note place="margin">Luk. 11. 4. 3. h. 13. 29.</note> the Iewes before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt / Chriſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> hymſelfe vſyng in hys ſmall companye to haue one to beare prouiſyon for the pore / the Apoſtles toke it vp in the church of Ieruſalem. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Paule not onely maketh mention of that<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. 6. 13.</note> offyce to the Romanes / ſhewing thereby that it was there / but he and Timothie ſaluteth them / wrytyng to the Philippians / ſhewing thereby<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 8.</note> that they were of great accompt. And wryting to Timothie / he preſcrybeth their election what <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> it ſhuld be / to direct not onely the choiſe of them / but to commend the vſe of them to the churche. And therfore ſuch ther muſt be procured in this Englyſhe church / as at thys day there is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed churches. Nowe to let paſſe the order of deacons at thys day / hauyng no ground out of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcryptures / but folyſhe / and accordyng to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe canons / whereby they may as well make them the biſhops garde / to defend hym when he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:11227:30"/> preacheth / as in thoſe canons they are / &amp; the eye of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> byſhop to loke about many things touching hys perſon / as thus employ them. To let paſſe to ſpeake thereof / ſeeing it is noted in the former treatiſes / thys I ſay further / that thys is God hys order for the pore / and none that wyll fyt it ſo well. Surely God be thanked for that care<note place="margin">The laſte ſtatute for the pore.</note> whych you haue had thys Parliament of the poore / and of the ſuppreſſyng of idle and wycked <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> vagaboundes / being in ſo good a way / it may be eaſie to practiſe thys way / to fortifie by law th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s courſe of the ſcriptures for the pores prouiſyon / and to continue that other braunche ſtill / for the ſuppreſſyng of idle and wycked vagabonds. For as touching the pore / whych are pore in deede / they muſt haue further prouiſion / &amp; further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort / then in dede can be procured by this ſtatute. For beſydes the naming and knowing of them / they are not enioyned to viſit and comfort them / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> wherby they myght be prouoked to godlyneſſe / they may ſeke and waite for their prouiſion / and peraduenture haue many a hard word to greeue them wyth / and no chriſtian conſolation / &amp; they may lacke many thyngs whych they oughte to haue. And theſe collectors ſhall not be ſubiect to the conſiſtorie / &amp; congregation / to geue accompt not only of the ſummes collected / but alſo whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue viſited the poore / and comforted them. For in the primitiue churche / there was <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> ſuche care had of the poore / that there were alſo widowes appoynted and maintained / that ſhuld<note place="margin">Widowes</note> waſhe / picke / and kepe the thyngs about y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pore / ſweete / and cleane / and intend them for their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries<note place="margin">1. tim. 5. 5</note> / that ſhould entertaine the pore ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that trauailed / and were driuen from place to place for then conſcience / and were not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to maintaine their owne charges / to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them I ſay / to bathe and waſhe their feete / 
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:11227:31"/> ſurbatted wyth going / and to intende to miniſter to them / the neceſſaryes there prouided by that church for that vſe. O godly care / and very chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cuſtome. I would / we wold in ſome part / in thys our great wealth and abundance / reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the care for the pore (our owne brethren / ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne fleſhe) whych the pore churches had in the time of their owne trouble / for the poore y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> then were amongſt them / and repaired fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to them / we ſhould not then thus vnnatural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> / hardly be drawne by lawe to paye that we are rated at / but we would willingly ſtretch out our purſſes / yea and ſtraine our ſelues farre / rather then eyther they of oure owne paryſhes / ſhoulde lacke any thing / or yet the afflicted churches of the ſtraungers / whiche are amongſte vs from<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tyed.</note> Fraunce / Flaunders / Italie / Spaine / or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place ſhould be deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itute / or lacke any thyng for their comfort. And yet God knoweth / moſte vnchriſtianly / and wakedly / many of vs cry out <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> againſt pore ſtrangers / as though we neuer had bene ſtraungers / nor were neuer releued by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or that we were not all of one body. Thanks be geuen to God for the Queenes maieſtie / and the counſel / and the reſt of the honourable / worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full / and others by whoſe meanes they are heere ſupported and maintained. And I am ſure of it / we all fare the better for it at God hys handes. And I beſeche the whole ſtate / &amp; beſeeche God / that the whole ſtare may bend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> more and more care for the godly ſtraungers y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> are of the churches in deede / and not to be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that they are ſo many / but to pitte their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent perſecution / and to comforte them. For the other ſwine that are not of the churches / I pray God they may fynde litle fauoure / except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent &amp; ioyne themſelues to the churches. Thus muche alſo of the Leacons. Thys order of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:11227:31"/> church gouernment / is grounded vpon that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our ſauioure. <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 18. 17. Num. 11.</note> Tei the churche / wherin it is certayne he alludeth to that conſiſtorie of the Iewes / and the ſcriptures that directe their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement. And it is ſo certain / that ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory they had / and ſuch elders / as it ſhall not<note place="margin">Deu. 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. chr. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Synedriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mat. 5. 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1. tim. 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> nede further to examine thoſe ſcryptures / but to come to the practiſe of the Apoſtles / &amp; the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by them. The apoſtle noteth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> are in the church bearing offyce / &amp; ruling / which ſhould be had in eſtimation for their offyce / two ſortes of elders and rulers / wherof the one ſort alſo ruleth / but they laboure in the woorde and doctrine to / and their offyce is the principall. He diſtinguiſheth them to the Corinthes / the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 28.</note> and the gouernoures / becauſe all gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures are not teachers / but becauſe al teachers are gouernoures / as to Timothie before is ſaid / ſo to the Romaines / deuiding the offyces of the<note place="margin">Rom. 11. 6. 7. 8.</note> churche into two ſortes / gouernment / and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> to the pore. To the firſt office he aſſigneth doctors / paſtors / and gouernors / calling them by theſe names / teachers / exhorters / and rulers / and to the ſecond offyce / he aſſigneth deacons &amp; widowes / callyng the firſt thoſe that minyſter / and the widowes thoſe that ſhew mercy. Of the widowes I will ſay no further / but vpon lyke decaſyon it is God hys order. But for the other orders / they muſt be in all well ordered churches of Chriſtians. The Apoſtle Paul and Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas<note place="margin">Act. 14. 2</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> ſet ſuche order in the churches whyche they planted. It was ſo in the churches of Rome / of Cornith / of Epheſus. An order is ſette downe<note place="margin">Act. 20. 1</note> what me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they muſt be. How they are to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen / the miniſters / the aſſiſtantes / the deacons / yea and the widowes / is declared in the Actes of the Apoſtles / and the epiſtle to Timothie / as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſore is noted. Howe they are to procede againſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:11227:32"/> offenders / is declared by our ſauioure / and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed<note place="margin">Math. 18. 15. 16. 17. 2. Theſ. 3. 14. 15. 1. Cor. 5. 4. 5. 2. Cor. 2. 7. 8. 1. Cor. 11. 16. 1. Cor. 14. 40. Act. 15.</note> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Theſſalonians / &amp; the Corinths / and likewyſe of the receiuing agayne of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate perſone / and howe they ſhould vſe hym while he abydeth excommunicate. And the ordering of things comely / and remouing abuſes euery one to keepe hymſelfe wythin his vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / ſo playne y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> places be that it nedeth no more / but that it would pleaſe you to reade them / and waighe them. And in lyke ſorte for conferences <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> and councels to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ale for the ſtay of the churches in true doctrine / and in godly order and quyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Corinthes it is plaine / and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at Ieruſalem / wherein is dealt for all thoſe cauſes of the churches at once. The perſons that were ſent to the councel / the perſons that chefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealt / and how / and the generall conſent of the Apoſtles / Elders / and brethren / would be well obſerued / as geuing great light for many purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Well / now who are our doers in this church <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> gouernment? how are they choſen? what cauſes doe they deale in? and how do they deale? In eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">What or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue / and what oure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates maye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n lawe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> pariſhe a conſiſtorie there is not / nor in euery great towne containing many paryſhes / nor in euery ſhire / but onely one in a dioceſſe / whych contayneth diuers ſhires. I may peraduenture d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deceyued / for there may be ſo many in adio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe / as there are Archdeaconries / beſydes the graund conſiſtorie of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> byſhop / or his ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtitute the Chauncellor / for they ſay the Archdeacon or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> his ſubſtitute y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> officiall / may viſite oftner then y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> biſhop / &amp; kepe courts oftner then y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Chancellor / &amp; there are in ſome dioceſſe diuers Archdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. But what of all thys? whence haue they their aucthoritie? who called them? what cauſes deale they in? and how? of God they haue not their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie / they hold it by the Canon lawe / and by the biſhop. And ſome of them pay the biſhop full
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:11227:32"/> well for it / they ſay. And ſo they ſay / that Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors offyces are ſo gainfull / that ſome of them are in fee wyth their byſhops for them / yea they ſay ſome biſhops haue payed for their byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricks other wayes / though not to the Quene / and that ſome of them haue large fees going out of their biſhopprickes / to their frends that holpe them to their preferments. Theſe are not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called. And whereas there is a ſtatute to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouche <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> thys calling and aucthoritie that the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops vſurpe / the ſtatute may make it good by lawe to holde ſuche titles and dignities / but not before God. I haue ſpoken of it before / and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miniſters muſt be equall / and the order muſt be / that ſome muſt be gouerned by all / and not all by ſome in the church gouernment / then y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame argument is of force againſt Archdeacons / and all ſuch highe prelates / which is agaynſt Lorde byſhops / Lord byſhops (I ſay) for the name bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is not the name of a Lord / but of a painfull <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> miniſter / and paſtor / or teacher: and yet in deede<note place="margin">Biſhop in Englande is the only name of a Lord mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter / but in ſcrypture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is no lorde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> name at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> in England euery byſhop is a Lorde. I knowe the common people would maruel / yea / and ioly wyſe men too / if they heard their paſtor ſay / I am your byſhop / a byſhoppe on God hys name / when were you made Lorde / and ſo take him to be proude / for no man is a byſhop heere / but he is alſo a Lord / whych thyng I ſay / becauſe I doe not meane that the ſcripture alloweth not a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop / but not a Lord byſhop. A byſhop or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> / or paſtor / and teacher in euery congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſcripture doth allowe / and hym or them to be the principal of the conſiſtorie of their congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation it doth allowe / but thys hyghe Prelacie it alloweth not / but forbiddeth it vtterly. Nowe then / ſeeing they haue no lawfull callyng / howe can they deale in any cauſes lawfully? but yet they doe deale / though not lawfully before God / 
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:11227:33"/> and that in infinite cauſes. And the proctors and doctors of that law / ſay the ſtudie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe is infinite / becauſe the cauſes are infinite / one I trow en gendering another / and ſo ſurely are the delayes and fees of thoſe courtes infinite. They haue to examine all tranſgreſſions agaynſte the boke of common prayer / the iniunctions / the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements / the canons / the metropoliticall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles / the biſhops articles of the dioceſſe / all the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> ſpirituall cauſes (as they call them) of the whole dioceſſe / or euery Archdeacon of hys circuite / and the Archbiſhop of hys prouince / and the Arches of the whole realme / and for certayne cauſes the prerogatiue court of my Lord his grace of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie / is ouer the realme alſo. Alſo of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all / yea and many carnall cauſes alſo / and that ſo handled / that it woulde greeue a chaſte earc / to heare the bawdie pleading of many proctors and doctors in thoſe courtes / and the ſumners / yea / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> and the regiſters themſelues / maſter Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con / and maſter Chauncellor / are eiten faine to<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nchaſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leading.</note> laughe it oute many times / when they can keepe their countenance no longer. An vnchaſt kinde of pleading of vnchaſt maters. They haue much adoe in marriage matters: when folke maye not marrie: what degrees may not marrie / and much more adoe about diuorcements / then either God or equitie would / reſtraining bothe parties from marriage / as long as they bothe are aliue togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> Beſides they haue the triall of titles to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices / and trial of tithes / &amp; trial of teſtaments / and by their high commiſſyon they may do many moe things / and vſe other then ſpirituall coerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as they call it) they may do what they will / ſauing life (I thinke) beat / priſon / punyſh by the purſe / baniſhe / &amp; I wot not what? All perſons / dicares and curates / all church wardens / all ſide men / ſworne men / and many forſworne / and all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:11227:33"/> paryſhes are at their commaundement. They<note place="margin">A large ſcope.</note> may commaund al Matres / Bailiffes / Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles / and ſuch like officers. All perſons are open to them / all iaylors obay them / receiue their pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners / and hamper them as they enioyne them. They haue good cauſes and bad brought before them / and puniſh both ſometimes / but the worſt ſeldomeſt &amp; leaſt / and the beſt ofteneſt and moſte. Many of their cauſes / &amp; much of their dealings <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> are declared in the former treatiſes / therefore I wil be but brefe. And thus I ſay / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> neither they / nor any order we haue in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this day doth / or can do that / which only God his order can do / and was appoynted to do. Neither their prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cials / nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole courſe of their canon lawe / nor their articles / nor commiſſions / can rightly order Chriſtes church / nor any ſtatute auaileth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto / but only that lawe / which bindeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole land to God hys orders for the gouerning of hys <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> church. And therfore to make lawes it auayleth not / ſaue mere ciuil / as in thys caſe (which they count ſpiritual) for the prouiſyon of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry / &amp; a law to ſtablyſh a ryght reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drawn<note place="margin">Conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio houſe.</note> out of the ſcriptures. I would leaue to ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further of their conuocation houſe / bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of it depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vpon the other houſes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament / and my lords the biſhops pleaſures / for nothyng they doe but for a faſhion / vntyll they come to the ſubſidie / and they haue had prety de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> to ſtop their doing / they haue had an order ere now to ſpeake nothing but latin / which was<note place="margin">Clarkes of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament houſe.</note> the way for many to tell but ſhort tales / for fear of ſhame. But yet among abuſes of theſe clergye men / thys is a great one / the whole houſe is a great abuſe / but the polling of their cleargye for their clarkes fees / and theyr diſorderous chuſing of their clarkes may be numbred among the reſt of their enormities / following none other order / 
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:11227:34"/> but for the face of a thyng / ſauing only my Lord byſhops pleaſure / or elſe he will know why / and yet it ſhalbe as he wil / when at is done / for either his Archdeacon ſhal haue one roume to beare his charges wythall / whych otherwiſe muſt be there Ex officio / &amp; ſo ware hys owne charges / or ſome other of hys frends ſhall haue that roume / &amp; hys Chancellor ſhall haue the other to pleaſure hym wyth / not for any pleaſure commonly y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellor can do in thys houſe / who ca ſcarſe ſay (as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> they ſay) ſhue to a gooſe / and if they had neede of<note place="margin">Clarkly deuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> a deuines anſwer or hym / wing moſt commonly a dudging Canoniſt / &amp; ſometime a Doctor. But when he is beſt / beſt is to bad. Thus I ſay / for thys matter the byſhop dealeth / or to teſtowe it vpon hys chapleyne / whych ſhall wayte at the ſtirrop / or at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> brydle / to buy hym a new gowne / &amp; ſomewhat wyth / but as vnfit for the houſe as the former commonly / but the byſhop wyll haue the apoynting of bothe ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. O the tyrannie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> that they vſe many / many wayes. I haue thus brefely as I could / and handling matters as I ought / paſſed through many abuſes in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery / and gouernment of the church of Chriſt in England / and I haue accordyng to my pore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent declared / what ſhoulde be the ſtate of a well ordered and reformed church. How many ſortes of miniſters / how they ſhuld be called to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / what their effice is / what order ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them / what metings &amp; conferences there <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> ſhould be for the continuing of true religion / and for them to increaſe in knowledge by. And in like ſorte I haue waded in declaring what offycers there ſhould be in the gouernment / what ſtroke they may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are / ſo it be by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation / what a conſiſtorie is / what excommunication is / what prouiſion there ſhuld be made for the pore / what the deacons office is / and or al other orders of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:11227:34"/> conſiſtorie / which it pleaſed God that I had in mynde / and thought moſt profitable to vtter. It remayneth for me now to returne agayne to the ſtate. To the Queenes moſt excellent maieſtie / the hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> able Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>rs / all the Nobilitie &amp; all the worſhypfull Commons of thys realme. And I humbly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſeeche her Maieſtie in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall<note place="margin">Appeale.</note> to vouchſafe the hearyng of vs / and lyke as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> make our appeare from the L. byſhops to be vprightly heard / what may be ſayd of our partes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> further / and more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ghly in thys matter of Gods / by diuers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no ſmall learning and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>tie of li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e / ſo it will pleaſe her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie / and you all / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erem to accept our appeale / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> not only we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> jus be oppreſſed / &amp; wrung<note place="margin">Vrgent cauſes.</note> as we are / againſt all equale and conſcience / but alſo that God hys cauſe ſhould not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo troden vnder foote / the benefite of hys churche ſo lyttle regarded / ſuche daily contentions raiſed by / and not pacified / ſuch greeuing of godly mennes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> / &amp; they not releeued. In ſo quiera raigne of our ſoueraigne / that Papiſts for pitie are not much diſquieted / and yet there ſhould be a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of pore chriſtians / and the profeſſors of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel ſuffered not farre vnlike to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e articles<note place="margin">The ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xe Articles.</note> whych cratty heades deuiſed / and prought y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> king her noble father vnto as they wold do her maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie how. That we ſhould haue God his cauſe by vs truely and faithfully propounded / &amp; by others wyckedly oppugned / and withſtode / &amp; yet it may <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> not by vs againe be maintained wythout great per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l. We beſeeche you to pitie thys caſe / and to prouide for it. It is the caſe already of manye a thouſand in this land / yea it is the caſe of as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as ſeeke the Lord aright / &amp; deſire to haue hys owne orders reſtored. Great troubles will come of it / if it be not prouided for / euen the ſame God that hath ſtirred me / a man vnknowne to ſpeake / 
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:11227:35"/> thoughe thoſe poore men which are locked vp in Newgate / neither do / nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſuffred to ſpeake / wil dayly ſtir vp moas yet vnknown / though I wer knowne &amp; an hundred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o / wel able to write and ſpeake in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter. Except you will profeſſe to perſecute vs (whych we hope her maieſtie of her wonted rare clemencie will not ſuffer though no doubt ſhe ſhalbe by many importunately ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited / and in manner forced) our cauſe vnheard / we do require and humbly beſeche you / if by theſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> bokes you be not reſolued what to do / yet to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for our ſafetie / &amp; giue vs the hearyng. They would beare men in hand that we deſpiſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie / and contemne lawes / but they ſhamefully ſlaunder vs to you / that ſo ſay. For it is her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties authoritie we ſlye to / as the ſupreme go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates authoritie / and the lawes we flie to.</note> in all cauſes / &amp; ouer all perſones within her dominions appoynted by God / and we flie to the lawes of this realme / the bonds of all peace &amp; good orders in thys la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And we beſeche her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> to haue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hearing of thys matter of Gods / and to take the defence of it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her. And to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie it by law / that it may be receiued by common order throughout her dominions. For though the orders be / &amp; ought to be drawne out of the booke of God / yet it is hir maieſtie that by hir princely authoritie ſhuld ſee euery of theſe things put in practiſe / and puniſh thoſe that neglect them / ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king lawes therfore / for the churche maye keepe theſe orders / but neuer in peace / except y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> and bleſſed aſſiſtance of the ſtates &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners linke in to ſee them accepted in their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys / and vſed. For otherwiſe the churche may and muſt keepe God hys orders / but alwayes in troubles and perſecution / whych is lyke to light vpon vs / except a reformation of Religion / or a direct Prouiſo for vs be made / for ſurely onely thys is God his order / &amp; ought to be vſed in hys
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:11227:35"/> church / ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in conſcience we are forced to ſpeake for it / and to vſe it / &amp; in conſcience / &amp; in the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God / we are forced to ſpeake as we doe of that reformation / which we now vſe / not ſo much for oughte elſe / as to ſet out the deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties therof / that we might thinke vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them. It is ſhewed in the former treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / how we thynke of the time and the perſons / when / and by whome it was firſt made and auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed: yea &amp; we know / that hetherunto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſtate <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> that now is / hath not bene ſufficiently inſtructed in any better then they vſe / wherfore we lay the fault where the fault is / vpon the biſhops / &amp; that ſort who are ſo ſoft ſet / &amp; fat fed / that they think they cannot better themſelues by god his orders / not for worldly eaſe &amp; pompe / and therefore they neyther haue dealt / nor will deale themſelues / to chaunge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe / nor for ought I ſee / wil ſuffer any other to deale / but their authoritie &amp; frendes ſhall fayle them / but they wyll oppreſſe them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> They pretend much y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> her maieſtie is ſore bent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not ſo much their doing: if y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> were ſo / then ſhould they themſelues deale for<note place="margin">Quarel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> vs to her maieſtie / and ceaſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> courſe they haue gon. But we know becauſe it moſt toucheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / they muſt hate vs. Wherefore we beſeeche your godly wiſdomes to haue conſideration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / and not to leaue vs in their daunger / nor in danger of ſuch iuſtices &amp; other / which be glad to haue a quarell to vs for oure conſcience / which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> can finde none in oure liues / enditing vs / fyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs. &amp;c. Now it is thus propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto you / if it ſeeme ſtrange &amp; harde to you (as no dout to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are not acquainted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mater it wil do / bicauſe they are better acquainted wyth another courſe / we beſeche you to ſuffer / &amp; to procure it to be further diſcuſſed by free conference among the learned men in this realme. There are many
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:11227:36"/> well able to doe it / &amp; wil be ready to doe it / if they<note place="margin">Certaine obiectious anſwered.</note> were called vpon / &amp; ſo ſhall you haue ſufficient light. There be that ſay. It wil be troublous to procede in theſe thyngs by publique authoritie / &amp; that it cannot be done. I wold deſire them y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſay ſo <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to remember how troublous it is / and wil be the while / to many good conſciences / &amp; how that God cannot but be hyghly diſpleaſed in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> meane tyme / &amp; how y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he cannot but reuenge thys trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> / that is raiſed againſt pore men hys faithfull ſeruaunts. There are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſay this order cannot be throughout a realme / we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not erect a conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in euery towne / we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not finde in euery town faithful men / &amp; ſome p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſh hathe ſmall choiſe of any kinde of men. Surely there would be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what thought of the vniting of ſmall pariſhes in one. But yet there is no pariſh ſo ſmall / but if it haue nede of Chriſt / and to be ſaued / then it hath nede of Chriſtes orders. And there is no ſubiect <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> (though in deede it be a raw time for to fynde in moſte pariſhes a competent number of faithfull me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deale / or to haue ſkil to deale in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters / there is no ſubiect I ſay / but if (making y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt choiſe) he wer choſen as it is directed afore / and a great penaltie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to deale in it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully / but he could not chuſe but deale in it / &amp; that truſtely &amp; wel / ſo that withall there wer drawne certaine general orders / to direct him or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how to deale / &amp; an honeſt learned paſtor placed ouer euery ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ocke. But ſome ſay it wil be hard to finde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> a preacher ſuch a one as I ſpake of before for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery pariſh to furniſh the realme any thing like. To thys I ſay / vſe thoſe you haue. Firſt place in manner as afore / all your biſhops in benefices / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> be of a ſound religion / and you ſhall furniſh ſo many benefices as they be in nombre / for they haue none. Yet they ſay / ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſome benefices / as I ſayde before to amende their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:11227:36"/> wythall. Beſides / vſe all you haue abrode which be fit for it / and in the vniuerſities. And let ſuch exerciſes be taken vp / as I haue ſpoken of / and let the towardlieſt of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> already haue bene in benefices / if they wil be content to goe to their bokes / &amp; afterward be employed vppon the miniſterie / let them be ſent to the vniuerſities / or ſuch like places / and be prouided for / by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they may procede in learning. And you <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> know not the ſtore y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> God will raiſe you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhort time / if you go about this godly purpoſe through<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. Take order y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thoſe faithfull miniſters which you haue / may be placed in the greateſt congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations. And for the ſacraments / let thoſe pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are yet vnprouided / repair to the pariſhes next adioyning y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> are prouided of paſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may vſe the ſacraments as they ought / not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the preaching of the word ſo that they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be examined &amp; allowed / as in that churche <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> wherto they ſhall reſort / they ſhall finde it orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> / til preachers increaſe to furniſh the places vnfurniſhed / if vpon confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence among the learned / it be thought meete / let<note place="margin">What prayer ſhould be made.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places vnfurniſhed be appoynted ſome diſcrete man / or to make ſome entier prayer / publiquely wyth them for all the churche / thys realme / oure ſoueraigne / the ſtate / and the particular occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of that congregation / for ſuche prayer ſhoulde be<note place="margin">Patrons / preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions &amp; inductions now vſed muſt ceaſe.</note> made. He maieſtie / and other that haue had the gift of benefices are to be deſired to depart with it that in manner as afore / the choiſe of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may be free / without al corruption / the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter being ſoughte and receyued for hys fytneſſe only. For the contrary cannot be continued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great tyrannie exerciſed ouer the Churche of God / and many corruptions neceſſarily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>oent therupon. Thus will I conclude / deſiring them that thinke I haue bene too round wyth the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:11227:37"/>
/ and that ſort / to remember howe rounde they are with vs / and how cruel / and againe how iuſt my ſpeach is / and further how it concerneth them not / any longer then they kepe thys trade / no more then the vpbraiding of popiſhe prieſtes / which toucheth not thoſe which haue renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced it / and I deſire thoſe that amongſte themſelues haue a right remorſe of God hys glory / and the churches good / to giue ouer / that we may bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly ioyne together / and be holpen by the good <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> giftes which God hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. And we ſhal prayſe God for them wyth all our heartes. And oure admonitions / oure God knoweth / hathe no worſe meaning. And I beſeeche him ſo to bleſſe our labour / and thoſe that deale in this his cauſe / that though our ſinnes deſerue no increaſe / yet for hys Chriſtes ſake pardoning vs / we maye euery day be more and more lightned in godlye iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / and ſtirred to embrace godlineſſe / that as we profeſſe to be hys churche / we may keepe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> hym our louing God and father / and be kept by hym to be hys obedient ſeruauntes and ſonnes / here to ſerue hym / &amp; after to inherite with him / that crowne purchaſed and promiſed vnto vs of hys owne great vnſpeakeable mercies in Chriſt hys ſonne our deare ſauioure / euer to praiſe and magnifie hym in that eternall bleſſedneſſe and glory / being God moſte hyghe and vnſearchable in hys wiſedome and iudgements. To whom be all prayſe / power / and dominion aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> &amp; yeelded as is right / and due nowe / and for euer. So be it.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Galath. 6. 7.</bibl>
               <q>Be not deceiued: God is not mocked: for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a man ſoweth / that ſhall he alſo reape.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11227:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE Articles, collected and taken (as it is thought) by the Byſhops our of a litle boke entituled an admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the Parliament / wyth an Anſwere to the ſame. Containing a confirmation of the ſayde Booke in ſhorte notes.</p>
            <bibl>Eſay. 5. 20.</bibl>
            <q>Woe be vnto them that ſpeake good of euill / and euill of good / whych put darkneſſe for light / and light for darkneſſe / that putte bytter for ſweete and ſweete for ſower.</q>
            <lg>
               <head>The Prynter to the Reader.</head>
               <l>Thys worke is fyniſhed thankes be to God / </l>
               <l>And he only wil keepe vs from the ſearchers rod.</l>
               <l>And though maſter Day and Toy watch &amp; warde / </l>
               <l>We hope the liuing God is our ſauegarde.</l>
               <l>Let them ſeeke / loke / and doe now what they can / </l>
               <l>It is but inuentions / and pollicies of man.</l>
               <l>But you wil maruel where it was fyniſhed / </l>
               <l>And you ſhal know (perchance) when domes day is ended / </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Imprinted we know where / and whan / </l>
               <l>Iudge you the place and you can.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. C. I. S</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
